<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/TAN-T.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/TAN.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TAN-T xmlns="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns" id="tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-t:ar.cat.eng.1926.edghill:semantic-refs" TAN-version="2021">
   <head>
      <name>Categories, Aristotle, English translation by E. M. Edghill</name>
      <master-location href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textalign/TAN-2021/master/examples/ar.cat.eng.1926.edghill.ref-logical.xml"/>
      <license licensor="kalvesmaki">
         <IRI>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en_US</IRI>
         <name>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</name>
         <desc>Exclusive of rights held and licenses offered by rightsholders of the source or
            sources listed below, this data file, insofar as it constitutes an independent work, is
            licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</desc>
      </license>
      <work>
         <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Categories_(Aristotle)</IRI>
         <name>Aristotle, Categories</name>
      </work>
      <source>
         <IRI>http://id.lib.harvard.edu/aleph/007901738/catalog</IRI>
         <name>Aristotle: Categoriae &amp; De interpretatione by E.M. Edghill. Analytica priora / by
            A.J. Jenkinson. Analytica posteriora / by G.R.G. Mure. Oxford : Clarendon Press, 1926.
         </name>
      </source>
      <model>
         <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-t:ar.cat.grc.1949.minio-paluello:semantic-refs</IRI>
         <name>Categories, Aristotle, Greek text by Minio-Paluello</name>
         <location href="ar.cat.grc.1949.minio-paluello.ref-logical.xml" accessed-when="2016-02-10T14:08:52.058-05:00"/>
      </model>
      <see-also relationship="alt">
         <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-t:ar.cat.grc.1949.minio-paluello:object-refs</IRI>
         <name>Categories, Aristotle, Greek text by Minio-Paluello</name>
         <location href="ar.cat.grc.1949.minio-paluello.ref-scriptum.xml" accessed-when="2016-02-11T12:40:42.823-05:00"/>
      </see-also>
      <redivision>
         <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-t:ar.cat.eng.1926.edghill:model-object-refs</IRI>
         <name>Categories, Aristotle, English translation by E. M. Edghill</name>
         <location href="ar.cat.eng.1926.edghill.ref-scriptum.xml" accessed-when="2016-06-22T08:13:35.791-04:00"/>
      </redivision>
      <adjustments>
         <normalization which="no hyphens"/>
      </adjustments>
      <vocabulary-key>
         <algorithm xml:id="xslt2">
            <IRI>tag:textalign.net,2015:stylesheet:convert-tan2018-to-tan2020</IRI>
            <name>Stylesheet to create a TAN file.</name>
            <location href="../applications/convert/convert%20TAN%202018%20to%20TAN%202020.xsl" accessed-when="2018-08-04T23:55:36.096-04:00"/>
         </algorithm>
         <div-type xml:id="ch">
            <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Chapter_(books)</IRI>
            <name>chapter</name>
         </div-type>
         <div-type xml:id="par">
            <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Paragraph</IRI>
            <name xml:lang="eng">paragraph</name>
         </div-type>
         <div-type xml:id="s">
            <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Sentence_(linguistics)</IRI>
            <name>sentence</name>
         </div-type>
         <div-type xml:id="ic">
            <IRI>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent_clause</IRI>
            <name>independent clause</name>
            <desc>used to identify two or more sentence parts that have a subject and predicate and
               function as a sentence.</desc>
         </div-type>
         <div-type xml:id="pt" which="part"/>
         <person xml:id="kalvesmaki">
            <IRI>http://viaf.org/viaf/299582703</IRI>
            <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:self</IRI>
            <name xml:lang="eng">Joel Kalvesmaki</name>
         </person>
         <algorithm xml:id="xslt1">
            <IRI>tag:textalign.net,2015:stylesheet:convert-tan2017-to-tan2018</IRI>
            <name>Stylesheet to populate a TAN-A file from collections.</name>
            <location href="../applications/convert/convert%20TAN%202017%20to%20TAN%202018.xsl" accessed-when="2018-08-05"/>
         </algorithm>
         <role xml:id="editor">
            <IRI>http://schema.org/editor</IRI>
            <name xml:lang="eng">Editor</name>
         </role>
         <role xml:id="stylesheet1" which="stylesheet"/>
         <relationship xml:id="alt">
            <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:relationship:diff-work-version</IRI>
            <name>different work version</name>
         </relationship>
      </vocabulary-key>
      <file-resp who="kalvesmaki"/>
      <resp who="xslt2" roles="stylesheet1"/>
      <resp roles="editor" who="kalvesmaki"/>
      <resp who="xslt1" roles="stylesheet1"/>
      <change when="2020-12-31" who="kalvesmaki">Added new reference-system declaration.</change>
      <change when="2016-06-22T08:04:25.003-04:00" who="kalvesmaki">Reformatted according to first
         model found. Backup made at
         file:/C:/Users/jdkalv/Dropbox/TAN/library/TAN-2018/examples/ar.cat.eng.1926.edghill.sem-201606220804250030400.xml.</change>
      <change when="2016-01-26-04:00" who="kalvesmaki">Started new file.</change>
      <change who="xslt1" when="2017-11-02T22:29:17.742-04:00">TAN file updated to 2018 schemas.</change>
      <change who="xslt2" when="2018-08-04T23:55:36.096-04:00">Converted from 2018 to 2019 schemas.</change>
      <to-do/>
   </head>
   <body xml:lang="eng">
      <div type="ch" n="1">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Things are said to be named 'equivocally' when, though they have
                  a common name, the definition corresponding with the name differs for each. Thus,
                  a real man and a figure in a picture can both lay claim to the name
                  'animal';</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">yet these are equivocally so named, for, though they have a
                  common name, the definition corresponding with the name differs for each.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">For should any one define in what sense each is an animal, his
                  definition in the one case will be appropriate to that case only.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">On the other hand, things are said to be named 'univocally'
                  which have both the name and the definition answering to the name in common. A man
                  and an ox are both 'animal',</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">and these are univocally so named, inasmuch as not only the
                  name, but also the definition, is the same in both cases:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for if a man should state in what sense each is an animal, the
                  statement in the one case would be identical with that in the other.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Things are said to be named 'derivatively', which derive their
                  name from some other name, but differ from it in termination. Thus the grammarian
                  derives his name from the word 'grammar', and the courageous man from the word
                  'courage'.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="2">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Forms of speech are either simple or composite.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Examples of the latter are such expressions as 'the man runs',
                  'the man wins';</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">of the former 'man', 'ox', 'runs', 'wins'.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="2">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Of things themselves some are predicable of a subject, and are
                  never present in a subject. Thus 'man' is predicable of the individual man, and is
                  never present in a subject.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">By being 'present in a subject' I do not mean present as parts
                  are present in a whole, but being incapable of existence apart from the said
                  subject. Some things, again, are present in a subject, but are never predicable of
                  a subject. For instance, a certain point of grammatical knowledge is present in
                  the mind, but is not predicable of any subject; or again, a certain whiteness may
                  be present in the body (for colour requires a material basis), yet it is never
                  predicable of anything.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Other things, again, are both predicable of a subject and
                  present in a subject. Thus while knowledge is present in the human mind, it is
                  predicable of grammar.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">There is, lastly, a class of things which are neither present in
                  a subject nor predicable of a subject, such as the individual man or the
                  individual horse.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">But, to speak more generally, that which is individual and has
                  the character of a unit is never predicable of a subject. Yet in some cases there
                  is nothing to prevent such being present in a subject.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">Thus a certain point of grammatical knowledge is present in a
                  subject.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="3">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">When one thing is predicated of another, all that which is
                  predicable of the predicate will be predicable also of the subject.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Thus, 'man' is predicated of the individual man; but 'animal' is
                  predicated of 'man';</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">it will, therefore, be predicable of the individual man
                  also:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">for the individual man is both 'man' and 'animal'.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">If genera are different and co-ordinate, their differentiae are
                  themselves different in kind. Take as an instance the genus 'animal' and the genus
                  'knowledge'.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">'With feet', 'two-footed', 'winged', 'aquatic', are differentiae
                  of 'animal'; the species of knowledge are not distinguished by the same
                  differentiae.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">One species of knowledge does not differ from another in being
                  'two-footed'.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">But where one genus is subordinate to another, there is nothing
                  to prevent their having the same differentiae:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for the greater class is predicated of the lesser, so that all
                  the differentiae of the predicate will be differentiae also of the subject.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="4">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Expressions which are in no way composite signify substance,
                  quantity, quality, relation, place, time, position, state, action, or
                  affection.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">To sketch my meaning roughly, examples of substance are 'man' or
                  'the horse',</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">of quantity, such terms as 'two cubits long' or 'three cubits
                  long',</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">of quality, such attributes as 'white', 'grammatical'.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">'Double', 'half', 'greater', fall under the category of
                  relation;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">'in a the market place', 'in the Lyceum', under that of
                  place;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">'yesterday', 'last year', under that of time.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="7">'Lying', 'sitting', are terms indicating position,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="8">'shod', 'armed', state;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="9">'to lance', 'to cauterize', action;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="10">'to be lanced', 'to be cauterized', affection.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">No one of these terms, in and by itself, involves an
                  affirmation; it is by the combination of such terms that positive or negative
                  statements arise.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For every assertion must, as is admitted, be either true or
                  false, whereas expressions which are not in any way composite such as 'man',
                  'white', 'runs', 'wins', cannot be either true or false.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="5">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Substance, in the truest and primary and most definite sense of
                  the word, is that which is neither predicable of a subject nor present in a
                  subject; for instance, the individual man or horse.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">But in a secondary sense those things are called substances
                  within which, as species, the primary substances are included; also those which,
                  as genera, include the species.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For instance, the individual man is included in the species
                  'man', and the genus to which the species belongs is 'animal';</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">these, therefore-that is to say, the species 'man' and the genus
                  'animal,-are termed secondary substances.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is plain from what has been said that both the name and the
                  definition of the predicate must be predicable of the subject.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For instance, 'man' is predicted of the individual man. Now in
                  this case the name of the species man' is applied to the individual, for we use
                  the term 'man' in describing the individual;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">and the definition of 'man' will also be predicated of the
                  individual man, for the individual man is both man and animal.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Thus, both the name and the definition of the species are
                  predicable of the individual.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">With regard, on the other hand, to those things which are
                  present in a subject, it is generally the case that neither their name nor their
                  definition is predicable of that in which they are present.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Though, however, the definition is never predicable, there is
                  nothing in certain cases to prevent the name being used.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">For instance, 'white' being present in a body is predicated of
                  that in which it is present, for a body is called white: the definition, however,
                  of the colour white' is never predicable of the body.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Everything except primary substances is either predicable of a
                  primary substance or present in a primary substance.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">This becomes evident by reference to particular instances which
                  occur.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">'Animal' is predicated of the species 'man', therefore of the
                  individual man, for if there were no individual man of whom it could be
                  predicated, it could not be predicated of the species 'man' at all.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Again, colour is present in body, therefore in individual
                  bodies,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">for if there were no individual body in which it was present, it
                  could not be present in body at all.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">Thus everything except primary substances is either predicated
                  of primary substances, or is present in them,</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">and if these last did not exist, it would be impossible for
                  anything else to exist.</div>
               <!-- Note that independent clauses 2 and 3 are missing; the English translation was made before Minio-Paluello's
                edition, which includes two clauses marked as 2b6a-c -->
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="2">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Of secondary substances, the species is more truly substance
                  than the genus,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">being more nearly related to primary substance.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">For if any one should render an account of what a primary
                  substance is, he would render a more instructive account, and one more proper to
                  the subject, by stating the species than by stating the genus.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Thus, he would give a more instructive account of an individual
                  man by stating that he was man than by stating that he was animal, for the former
                  description is peculiar to the individual in a greater degree, while the latter is
                  too general. Again, the man who gives an account of the nature of an individual
                  tree will give a more instructive account by mentioning the species 'tree' than by
                  mentioning the genus 'plant'.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Moreover, primary substances are most properly called substances
                  in virtue of the fact that they are the entities which underlie everything else,
                  and that everything else is either predicated of them or present in them.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Now the same relation which subsists between primary substance
                  and everything else subsists also between the species and the genus:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for the species is to the genus as subject is to
                  predicate,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">since the genus is predicated of the species, whereas the
                  species cannot be predicated of the genus.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">Thus we have a second ground for asserting that the species is
                  more truly substance than the genus.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Of species themselves, except in the case of such as are genera,
                  no one is more truly substance than another.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">We should not give a more appropriate account of the individual
                  man by stating the species to which he belonged, than we should of an individual
                  horse by adopting the same method of definition.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In the same way, of primary substances, no one is more truly
                  substance than another;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">an individual man is not more truly substance than an individual
                  ox.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="3">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is, then, with good reason that of all that remains, when we
                  exclude primary substances, we concede to species and genera alone the name
                  'secondary substance',</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for these alone of all the predicates convey a knowledge of
                  primary substance.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">For it is by stating the species or the genus that we
                  appropriately define any individual man; and we shall make our definition more
                  exact by stating the former than by stating the latter.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">All other things that we state, such as that he is white, that
                  he runs, and so on, are irrelevant to the definition.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">Thus it is just that these alone, apart from primary substances,
                  should be called substances.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Further, primary substances are most properly so called, because
                  they underlie and are the subjects of everything else.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Now the same relation that subsists between primary substance
                  and everything else subsists also between the species and the genus to which the
                  primary substance belongs, on the one hand, and every attribute which is not
                  included within these, on the other.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">For these are the subjects of all such.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">If we call an individual man 'skilled in grammar', the predicate
                  is applicable also to the species and to the genus to which he belongs.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">This law holds good in all cases.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="4">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is a common characteristic of all substance that it is never
                  present in a subject.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">For primary substance is neither present in a subject nor
                  predicated of a subject;</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">while, with regard to secondary substances, it is clear from the
                  following arguments (apart from others) that they are not present in a
                  subject.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For 'man' is predicated of the individual man, but is not
                  present in any subject: for manhood is not present in the individual man.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">In the same way, 'animal' is also predicated of the individual
                  man, but is not present in him.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Again, when a thing is present in a subject, though the name may
                  quite well be applied to that in which it is present, the definition cannot be
                  applied.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Yet of secondary substances, not only the name, but also the
                  definition, applies to the subject: we should use both the definition of the
                  species and that of the genus with reference to the individual man.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Thus substance cannot be present in a subject.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Yet this is not peculiar to substance, for it is also the case
                  that differentiae cannot be present in subjects.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">The characteristics 'terrestrial' and 'two-footed' are
                  predicated of the species 'man', but not present in it. For they are not in
                  man.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Moreover, the definition of the differentia may be predicated of
                  that of which the differentia itself is predicated.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For instance, if the characteristic 'terrestrial' is predicated
                  of the species 'man', the definition also of that characteristic may be used to
                  form the predicate of the species 'man': for 'man' is terrestrial.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="8">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The fact that the parts of substances appear to be present in
                  the whole, as in a subject, should not make us apprehensive lest we should have to
                  admit that such parts are not substances:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for in explaining the phrase 'being present in a subject', we
                  stated' that we meant 'otherwise than as parts in a whole'.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="5">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is the mark of substances and of differentiae that, in all
                  propositions of which they form the predicate, they are predicated
                  univocally.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For all such propositions have for their subject either the
                  individual or the species.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is true that, inasmuch as primary substance is not predicable
                  of anything, it can never form the predicate of any proposition.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">But of secondary substances, the species is predicated of the
                  individual, the genus both of the species and of the individual.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Similarly the differentiae are predicated of the species and of
                  the individuals.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Moreover, the definition of the species and that of the genus
                  are applicable to the primary substance, and that of the genus to the
                  species.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">For all that is predicated of the predicate will be predicated
                  also of the subject.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Similarly, the definition of the differentiae will be applicable
                  to the species and to the individuals.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">But it was stated above that the word 'univocal' was applied to
                  those things which had both name and definition in common.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is, therefore, established that in every proposition, of
                  which either substance or a differentia forms the predicate, these are predicated
                  univocally.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="6">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">All substance appears to signify that which is individual.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In the case of primary substance this is indisputably
                  true,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for the thing is a unit.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In the case of secondary substances, when we speak, for
                  instance, of 'man' or 'animal', our form of speech gives the impression that we
                  are here also indicating that which is individual,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">but the impression is not strictly true; for a secondary
                  substance is not an individual, but a class with a certain qualification; for it
                  is not one and single as a primary substance is; the words 'man', 'animal', are
                  predicable of more than one subject.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Yet species and genus do not merely indicate quality, like the
                  term 'white';</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">'white' indicates quality and nothing further, but species and
                  genus determine the quality with reference to a substance: they signify substance
                  qualitatively differentiated.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The determinate qualification covers a larger field in the case
                  of the genus that in that of the species:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">he who uses the word 'animal' is herein using a word of wider
                  extension than he who uses the word 'man'.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="7">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Another mark of substance is that it has no contrary.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">What could be the contrary of any primary substance, such as the
                  individual man or animal?</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It has none. Nor can the species or the genus have a
                  contrary.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Yet this characteristic is not peculiar to substance, but is
                  true of many other things, such as quantity.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">There is nothing that forms the contrary of 'two cubits long' or
                  of 'three cubits long', or of 'ten', or of any such term. A man may contend that
                  'much' is the contrary of 'little', or 'great' of 'small',</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">but of definite quantitative terms no contrary exists.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="8">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Substance, again, does not appear to admit of variation of
                  degree.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">I do not mean by this that one substance cannot be more or less
                  truly substance than another, for it has already been stated' that this is the
                  case; but that no single substance admits of varying degrees within itself.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">For instance, one particular substance, 'man', cannot be more or
                  less man either than himself at some other time or than some other man.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">One man cannot be more man than another, as that which is white
                  may be more or less white than some other white object, or as that which is
                  beautiful may be more or less beautiful than some other beautiful object.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">The same quality, moreover, is said to subsist in a thing in
                  varying degrees at different times. A body, being white, is said to be whiter at
                  one time than it was before, or, being warm, is said to be warmer or less warm
                  than at some other time.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">But substance is not said to be more or less that which it is: a
                  man is not more truly a man at one time than he was before, nor is anything, if it
                  is substance, more or less what it is.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Substance, then, does not admit of variation of degree.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="9">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The most distinctive mark of substance appears to be that, while
                  remaining numerically one and the same, it is capable of admitting contrary
                  qualities.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">From among things other than substance, we should find ourselves
                  unable to bring forward any which possessed this mark.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Thus, one and the same colour cannot be white and black. Nor can
                  the same one action be good and bad: this law holds good with everything that is
                  not substance.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">But one and the selfsame substance, while retaining its
                  identity, is yet capable of admitting contrary qualities.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">The same individual person is at one time white, at another
                  black, at one time warm, at another cold, at one time good, at another bad.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">This capacity is found nowhere else, though it might be
                  maintained that a statement or opinion was an exception to the rule.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">The same statement, it is agreed, can be both true and false.
                  For if the statement 'he is sitting' is true, yet, when the person in question has
                  risen, the same statement will be false.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">The same applies to opinions.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">For if any one thinks truly that a person is sitting, yet, when
                  that person has risen, this same opinion, if still held, will be false.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Yet although this exception may be allowed, there is,
                  nevertheless, a difference in the manner in which the thing takes place.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">It is by themselves changing that substances admit contrary
                  qualities. It is thus that that which was hot becomes cold, for it has entered
                  into a different state. Similarly that which was white becomes black, and that
                  which was bad good, by a process of change; and in the same way in all other cases
                  it is by changing that substances are capable of admitting contrary
                  qualities.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">But statements and opinions themselves remain unaltered in all
                  respects: it is by the alteration in the facts of the case that the contrary
                  quality comes to be theirs.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">The statement 'he is sitting' remains unaltered, but it is at
                  one time true, at another false, according to circumstances.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">What has been said of statements applies also to opinions.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Thus, in respect of the manner in which the thing takes place,
                  it is the peculiar mark of substance that it should be capable of admitting
                  contrary qualities; for it is by itself changing that it does so. If, then, a man
                  should make this exception and contend that statements and opinions are capable of
                  admitting contrary qualities,</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">his contention is unsound.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For statements and opinions are said to have this capacity, not
                  because they themselves undergo modification, but because this modification occurs
                  in the case of something else.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">The truth or falsity of a statement depends on facts, and not on
                  any power on the part of the statement itself of admitting contrary
                  qualities.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">In short, there is nothing which can alter the nature of
                  statements and opinions. As, then, no change takes place in themselves, these
                  cannot be said to be capable of admitting contrary qualities.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">But it is by reason of the modification which takes place within
                  the substance itself that a substance is said to be capable of admitting contrary
                  qualities;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">for a substance admits within itself either disease or health,
                  whiteness or blackness. It is in this sense that it is said to be capable of
                  admitting contrary qualities.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">To sum up, it is a distinctive mark of substance, that, while
                  remaining numerically one and the same, it is capable of admitting contrary
                  qualities, the modification taking place through a change in the substance
                  itself.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="8">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Let these remarks suffice on the subject of substance.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="6">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Quantity is either discrete or continuous.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Moreover, some quantities are such that each part of the whole
                  has a relative position to the other parts: others have within them no such
                  relation of part to part.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Instances of discrete quantities are number and speech; of
                  continuous, lines, surfaces, solids, and, besides these, time and place.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In the case of the parts of a number, there is no common
                  boundary at which they join.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For example: two fives make ten, but the two fives have no
                  common boundary, but are separate;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">the parts three and seven also do not join at any
                  boundary.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Nor, to generalize, would it ever be possible in the case of
                  number that there should be a common boundary among the parts; they are always
                  separate.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">Number, therefore, is a discrete quantity.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The same is true of speech.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">That speech is a quantity is evident:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for it is measured in long and short syllables.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">I mean here that speech which is vocal.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">Moreover, it is a discrete quantity for its parts have no common
                  boundary.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">There is no common boundary at which the syllables join, but
                  each is separate and distinct from the rest.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">A line, on the other hand, is a continuous quantity,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for it is possible to find a common boundary at which its parts
                  join.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">In the case of the line, this common boundary is the point; in
                  the case of the plane, it is the line: for the parts of the plane have also a
                  common boundary.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Similarly you can find a common boundary in the case of the
                  parts of a solid, namely either a line or a plane.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Space and time also belong to this class of quantities.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Time, past, present, and future, forms a continuous whole.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="8">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Space, likewise, is a continuous quantity;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for the parts of a solid occupy a certain space, and these have
                  a common boundary;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">it follows that the parts of space also, which are occupied by
                  the parts of the solid, have the same common boundary as the parts of the
                  solid.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Thus, not only time, but space also, is a continuous
                  quantity,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">for its parts have a common boundary.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="2">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Quantities consist either of parts which bear a relative
                  position each to each, or of parts which do not.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">The parts of a line bear a relative position to each other, for
                  each lies somewhere, and it would be possible to distinguish each, and to state
                  the position of each on the plane and to explain to what sort of part among the
                  rest each was contiguous.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Similarly the parts of a plane have position, for it could
                  similarly be stated what was the position of each and what sort of parts were
                  contiguous.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The same is true with regard to the solid and to space.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">But it would be impossible to show that the parts of a number
                  had a relative position each to each, or a particular position, or to state what
                  parts were contiguous.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Nor could this be done in the case of time,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for none of the parts of time has an abiding existence, and that
                  which does not abide can hardly have position.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It would be better to say that such parts had a relative order,
                  in virtue of one being prior to another.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Similarly with number: in counting, 'one' is prior to 'two', and
                  'two' to 'three',</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">and thus the parts of number may be said to possess a relative
                  order, though it would be impossible to discover any distinct position for
                  each.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">This holds good also in the case of speech.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">None of its parts has an abiding existence: when once a syllable
                  is pronounced, it is not possible to retain it, so that, naturally, as the parts
                  do not abide, they cannot have position.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Thus, some quantities consist of parts which have position, and
                  some of those which have not.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="3">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Strictly speaking, only the things which I have mentioned belong
                  to the category of quantity: everything else that is called quantitative is a
                  quantity in a secondary sense.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">It is because we have in mind some one of these quantities,
                  properly so called, that we apply quantitative terms to other things. We speak of
                  what is white as large, because the surface over which the white extends is large;
                  we speak of an action or a process as lengthy, because the time covered is
                  long;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">these things cannot in their own right claim the quantitative
                  epithet.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">For instance, should any one explain how long an action was, his
                  statement would be made in terms of the time taken, to the effect that it lasted a
                  year, or something of that sort. In the same way, he would explain the size of a
                  white object in terms of surface, for he would state the area which it
                  covered.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">Thus the things already mentioned, and these alone, are in their
                  intrinsic nature quantities; nothing else can claim the name in its own right,
                  but, if at all, only in a secondary sense.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="4">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Quantities have no contraries. In the case of definite
                  quantities this is obvious; thus, there is nothing that is the contrary of 'two
                  cubits long' or of 'three cubits long', or of a surface, or of any such
                  quantities. A man might, indeed, argue that 'much' was the contrary of 'little',
                  and 'great' of 'small'.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">But these are not quantitative, but relative;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">things are not great or small absolutely, they are so called
                  rather as the result of an act of comparison. For instance, a mountain is called
                  small, a grain large, in virtue of the fact that the latter is greater than others
                  of its kind, the former less.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Thus there is a reference here to an external standard, for if
                  the terms 'great' and 'small' were used absolutely, a mountain would never be
                  called small or a grain large.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Again, we say that there are many people in a village, and few
                  in Athens, although those in the city are many times as numerous as those in the
                  village: or we say that a house has many in it, and a theatre few, though those in
                  the theatre far outnumber those in the house.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The terms 'two cubits long, "three cubits long,' and so on
                  indicate quantity, the terms 'great' and 'small' indicate relation,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for they have reference to an external standard.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">It is, therefore, plain that these are to be classed as
                  relative.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Again, whether we define them as quantitative or not, they have
                  no contraries:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for how can there be a contrary of an attribute which is not to
                  be apprehended in or by itself, but only by reference to something external?</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Again, if 'great' and 'small' are contraries, it will come about
                  that the same subject can admit contrary qualities at one and the same time, and
                  that things will themselves be contrary to themselves.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">For it happens at times that the same thing is both small and
                  great. For the same thing may be small in comparison with one thing, and great in
                  comparison with another,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">so that the same thing comes to be both small and great at one
                  and the same time,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">and is of such a nature as to admit contrary qualities at one
                  and the same moment.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Yet it was agreed, when substance was being discussed, that
                  nothing admits contrary qualities at one and the same moment. For though substance
                  is capable of admitting contrary qualities, yet no one is at the same time both
                  sick and healthy, nothing is at the same time both white and black. Nor is there
                  anything which is qualified in contrary ways at one and the same time.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="8">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Moreover, if these were contraries, they would themselves be
                  contrary to themselves.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For if 'great' is the contrary of 'small', and the same thing is
                  both great and small at the same time, then 'small' or 'great' is the contrary of
                  itself.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">But this is impossible.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="9">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The term 'great', therefore, is not the contrary of the term
                  'small', nor 'much' of 'little'. And even though a man should call these terms not
                  relative but quantitative, they would not have contraries.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="10">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is in the case of space that quantity most plausibly appears
                  to admit of a contrary.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For men define the term 'above' as the contrary of 'below', when
                  it is the region at the centre they mean by 'below'; and this is so, because
                  nothing is farther from the extremities of the universe than the region at the
                  centre.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="11">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Indeed, it seems that in defining contraries of every kind men
                  have recourse to a spatial metaphor,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for they say that those things are contraries which, within the
                  same class, are separated by the greatest possible distance.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="5">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Quantity does not, it appears, admit of variation of degree. One
                  thing cannot be two cubits long in a greater degree than another.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Similarly with regard to number: what is 'three' is not more
                  truly three than what is 'five' is five; nor is one set of three more truly three
                  than another set.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Again, one period of time is not said to be more truly time than
                  another.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Nor is there any other kind of quantity, of all that have been
                  mentioned, with regard to which variation of degree can be predicated.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">The category of quantity, therefore, does not admit of variation
                  of degree.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="6">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The most distinctive mark of quantity is that equality and
                  inequality are predicated of it.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Each of the aforesaid quantities is said to be equal or unequal.
                  For instance, one solid is said to be equal or unequal to another; number, too,
                  and time can have these terms applied to them,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">indeed can all those kinds of quantity that have been
                  mentioned.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">That which is not a quantity can by no means, it would seem, be
                  termed equal or unequal to anything else. One particular disposition or one
                  particular quality, such as whiteness, is by no means compared with another in
                  terms of equality and inequality but rather in terms of similarity.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Thus it is the distinctive mark of quantity that it can be
                  called equal and unequal.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="7">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Those things are called relative, which, being either said to be
                  of something else or related to something else, are explained by reference to that
                  other thing.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For instance, the word 'superior' is explained by reference to
                  something else, for it is superiority over something else that is meant.
                  Similarly, the expression 'double' has this external reference, for it is the
                  double of something else that is meant.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">So it is with everything else of this kind.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">There are, moreover, other relatives, e.g. habit, disposition,
                  perception, knowledge, and attitude.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">The significance of all these is explained by a reference to
                  something else and in no other way.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Thus, a habit is a habit of something, knowledge is knowledge of
                  something, attitude is the attitude of something. So it is with all other
                  relatives that have been mentioned.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Those terms, then, are called relative, the nature of which is
                  explained by reference to something else, the preposition 'of' or some other
                  preposition being used to indicate the relation.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Thus, one mountain is called great in comparison with son with
                  another; for the mountain claims this attribute by comparison with something.
                  Again, that which is called similar must be similar to something else, and all
                  other such attributes have this external reference.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is to be noted that lying and standing and sitting are
                  particular attitudes, but attitude is itself a relative term.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">To lie, to stand, to be seated, are not themselves attitudes,
                  but take their name from the aforesaid attitudes.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="2">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is possible for relatives to have contraries. Thus virtue has
                  a contrary, vice, these both being relatives; knowledge, too, has a contrary,
                  ignorance.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">But this is not the mark of all relatives;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">'double' and 'triple' have no contrary, nor indeed has any such
                  term.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It also appears that relatives can admit of variation of
                  degree.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For 'like' and 'unlike', 'equal' and 'unequal', have the
                  modifications 'more' and 'less' applied to them, and each of these is relative in
                  character:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for the terms 'like' and 'unequal' bear a reference to something
                  external.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Yet, again, it is not every relative term that admits of
                  variation of degree.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">No term such as 'double' admits of this modification.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="3">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">All relatives have correlatives: by the term 'slave' we mean the
                  slave of a master, by the term 'master', the master of a slave; by 'double', the
                  double of its hall; by 'half', the half of its double; by 'greater', greater than
                  that which is less; by 'less,' less than that which is greater.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">So it is with every other relative term;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">but the case we use to express the correlation differs in some
                  instances. Thus, by knowledge we mean knowledge the knowable; by the knowable,
                  that which is to be apprehended by knowledge; by perception, perception of the
                  perceptible; by the perceptible, that which is apprehended by perception.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Sometimes, however, reciprocity of correlation does not appear
                  to exist. This comes about when a blunder is made, and that to which the relative
                  is related is not accurately stated.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">If a man states that a wing is necessarily relative to a bird,
                  the connexion between these two will not be reciprocal,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for it will not be possible to say that a bird is a bird by
                  reason of its wings.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">
                  <div type="pt" n="a">The reason is that the original statement was inaccurate, for
                     the wing is not said to be relative to the bird qua bird,</div>
               </div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">since many creatures besides birds have wings,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">
                  <div type="pt" n="b">but qua winged creature.</div>
               </div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">If, then, the statement is made accurate, the connexion will be
                  reciprocal, for we can speak of a wing, having reference necessarily to a winged
                  creature, and of a winged creature as being such because of its wings.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Occasionally, perhaps, it is necessary to coin words, if no word
                  exists by which a correlation can adequately be explained.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">If we define a rudder as necessarily having reference to a boat,
                  our definition will not be appropriate, for the rudder does not have this
                  reference to a boat qua boat,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">as there are boats which have no rudders.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Thus we cannot use the terms reciprocally,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">for the word 'boat' cannot be said to find its explanation in
                  the word 'rudder'.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">As there is no existing word, our definition would perhaps be
                  more accurate if we coined some word like 'ruddered' as the correlative of
                  'rudder'.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">If we express ourselves thus accurately, at any rate the terms
                  are reciprocally connected,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for the 'ruddered' thing is 'ruddered' in virtue of its
                  rudder.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">So it is in all other cases. A head will be more accurately
                  defined as the correlative of that which is 'headed', than as that of an
                  animal,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for the animal does not have a head qua animal,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">since many animals have no head.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Thus we may perhaps most easily comprehend that to which a thing
                  is related, when a name does not exist, if, from that which has a name, we derive
                  a new name, and apply it to that with which the first is reciprocally connected,
                  as in the aforesaid instances, when we derived the word 'winged' from 'wing' and
                  from 'rudder'.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">All relatives, then, if properly defined, have a
                  correlative.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">I add this condition because, if that to which they are related
                  is stated as haphazard and not accurately, the two are not found to be
                  interdependent.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="8">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Let me state what I mean more clearly. Even in the case of
                  acknowledged correlatives, and where names exist for each, there will be no
                  interdependence if one of the two is denoted, not by that name which expresses the
                  correlative notion, but by one of irrelevant significance.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">The term 'slave,' if defined as related, not to a master, but to
                  a man, or a biped, or anything of that sort,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">is not reciprocally connected with that in relation to which it
                  is defined, for the statement is not exact.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="9">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Further, if one thing is said to be correlative with another,
                  and the terminology used is correct, then, though all irrelevant attributes should
                  be removed, and only that one attribute left in virtue of which it was correctly
                  stated to be correlative with that other, the stated correlation will still
                  exist.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">If the correlative of 'the slave' is said to be 'the master',
                  then, though all irrelevant attributes of the said 'master', such as 'biped',
                  'receptive of knowledge', 'human', should be removed, and the attribute 'master'
                  alone left, the stated correlation existing between him and the slave will remain
                  the same,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for it is of a master that a slave is said to be the
                  slave.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="10">
               <div type="ic" n="1">On the other hand, if, of two correlatives, one is not correctly
                  termed, then, when all other attributes are removed and that alone is left in
                  virtue of which it was stated to be correlative, the stated correlation will be
                  found to have disappeared.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For suppose the correlative of 'the slave' should be said to be
                  'the man', or the correlative of 'the wing' 'the bird'; if the attribute 'master'
                  be withdrawn from' the man',</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">the correlation between 'the man' and 'the slave' will cease to
                  exist, for if the man is not a master, the slave is not a slave.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Similarly, if the attribute 'winged' be withdrawn from 'the
                  bird',</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">'the wing' will no longer be relative;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">for if the so-called correlative is not winged, it follows that
                  'the wing' has no correlative.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="11">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Thus it is essential that the correlated terms should be exactly
                  designated;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">if there is a name existing, the statement will be easy; if not,
                  it is doubtless our duty to construct names.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="12">
               <div type="ic" n="1">When the terminology is thus correct, it is evident that all
                  correlatives are interdependent.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="4">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Correlatives are thought to come into existence
                  simultaneously.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">This is for the most part true, as in the case of the double and
                  the half.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">The existence of the half necessitates the existence of that of
                  which it is a half. Similarly the existence of a master necessitates the existence
                  of a slave, and that of a slave implies that of a master;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">these are merely instances of a general rule.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Moreover, they cancel one another;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for if there is no double it follows that there is no
                  half,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">and vice versa; this rule also applies to all such
                  correlatives.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Yet it does not appear to be true in all cases that correlatives
                  come into existence simultaneously.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">The object of knowledge would appear to exist before knowledge
                  itself,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for it is usually the case that we acquire knowledge of objects
                  already existing;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">it would be difficult, if not impossible, to find a branch of
                  knowledge the beginning of the existence of which was contemporaneous with that of
                  its object.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Again, while the object of knowledge, if it ceases to exist,
                  cancels at the same time the knowledge which was its correlative, the converse of
                  this is not true.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">It is true that if the object of knowledge does not exist there
                  can be no knowledge: for there will no longer be anything to know. Yet it is
                  equally true that, if knowledge of a certain object does not exist, the object may
                  nevertheless quite well exist.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Thus, in the case of the squaring of the circle, if indeed that
                  process is an object of knowledge, though it itself exists as an object of
                  knowledge, yet the knowledge of it has not yet come into existence.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Again, if all animals ceased to exist, there would be no
                  knowledge, but there might yet be many objects of knowledge.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">This is likewise the case with regard to perception:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for the object of perception is, it appears, prior to the act of
                  perception.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">If the perceptible is annihilated, perception also will cease to
                  exist; but the annihilation of perception does not cancel the existence of the
                  perceptible.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="8">
               <div type="ic" n="1">For perception implies a body perceived and a body in which
                  perception takes place. Now if that which is perceptible is annihilated, it
                  follows that the body is annihilated, for the body is a perceptible thing; and if
                  the body does not exist, it follows that perception also ceases to exist. Thus the
                  annihilation of the perceptible involves that of perception.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="9">
               <div type="ic" n="1">But the annihilation of perception does not involve that of the
                  perceptible.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For if the animal is annihilated, it follows that perception
                  also is annihilated, but perceptibles such as body, heat, sweetness, bitterness,
                  and so on, will remain.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="10">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Again, perception is generated at the same time as the
                  perceiving subject, for it comes into existence at the same time as the animal.
                  But the perceptible surely exists before perception; for fire and water and such
                  elements, out of which the animal is itself composed, exist before the animal is
                  an animal at all, and before perception. Thus it would seem that the perceptible
                  exists before perception.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="5">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It may be questioned whether it is true that no substance is
                  relative, as seems to be the case, or whether exception is to be made in the case
                  of certain secondary substances.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">With regard to primary substances, it is quite true that there
                  is no such possibility,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for neither wholes nor parts of primary substances are
                  relative.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">The individual man or ox is not defined with reference to
                  something external.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Similarly with the parts:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">a particular hand or head is not defined as a particular hand or
                  head of a particular person, but as the hand or head of a particular person.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is true also, for the most part at least, in the case of
                  secondary substances;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">the species 'man' and the species 'ox' are not defined with
                  reference to anything outside themselves. Wood, again, is only relative in so far
                  as it is some one's property, not in so far as it is wood.</div>
            </div>
            <!-- bookmark -->
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is plain, then, that in the cases mentioned substance is not
                  relative. But with regard to some secondary substances there is a difference of
                  opinion;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">thus, such terms as 'head' and 'hand' are defined with reference
                  to that of which the things indicated are a part, and so it comes about that these
                  appear to have a relative character.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Indeed, if our definition of that which is relative was
                  complete, it is very difficult, if not impossible, to prove that no substance is
                  relative.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">If, however, our definition was not complete, if those things
                  only are properly called relative in the case of which relation to an external
                  object is a necessary condition of existence, perhaps some explanation of the
                  dilemma may be found.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The former definition does indeed apply to all relatives, but
                  the fact that a thing is explained with reference to something else does not make
                  it essentially relative.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">From this it is plain that, if a man definitely apprehends a
                  relative thing, he will also definitely apprehend that to which it is
                  relative.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="8">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Indeed this is self-evident:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for if a man knows that some particular thing is relative,
                  assuming that we call that a relative in the case of which relation to something
                  is a necessary condition of existence, he knows that also to which it is
                  related.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">For if he does not know at all that to which it is related, he
                  will not know whether or not it is relative.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="9">
               <div type="ic" n="1">This is clear, moreover, in particular instances.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">If a man knows definitely that such and such a thing is
                  'double', he will also forthwith know definitely that of which it is the double.
                  For if there is nothing definite of which he knows it to be the double, he does
                  not know at all that it is double.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Again, if he knows that a thing is more beautiful, it follows
                  necessarily that he will forthwith definitely know that also than which it is more
                  beautiful. He will not merely know indefinitely that it is more beautiful than
                  something which is less beautiful,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">for this would be supposition, not knowledge.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">For if he does not know definitely that than which it is more
                  beautiful,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">he can no longer claim to know definitely that it is more
                  beautiful than something else which is less beautiful: for it might be that
                  nothing was less beautiful.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="7">It is, therefore, evident that if a man apprehends some relative
                  thing definitely, he necessarily knows that also definitely to which it is
                  related.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="10">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Now the head, the hand, and such things are substances, and it
                  is possible to know their essential character definitely, but it does not
                  necessarily follow that we should know that to which they are related.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">It is not possible to know forthwith whose head or hand is
                  meant.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Thus these are not relatives,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">and, this being the case, it would be true to say that no
                  substance is relative in character.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="11">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is perhaps a difficult matter, in such cases, to make a
                  positive statement without more exhaustive examination, but to have raised
                  questions with regard to details is not without advantage.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="8">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">By 'quality' I mean that in virtue of which people are said to
                  be such and such.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Quality is a term that is used in many senses.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">One sort of quality let us call 'habit' or 'disposition'.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Habit differs from disposition in being more lasting and more
                  firmly established.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">The various kinds of knowledge and of virtue are habits,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for knowledge, even when acquired only in a moderate degree, is,
                  it is agreed, abiding in its character and difficult to displace, unless some
                  great mental upheaval takes place, through disease or any such cause.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">The virtues, also,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">such as justice, self-restraint, and so on, are not easily
                  dislodged or dismissed, so as to give place to vice.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">By a disposition, on the other hand, we mean a condition that is
                  easily changed and quickly gives place to its opposite. Thus, heat, cold, disease,
                  health, and so on are dispositions.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For a man is disposed in one way or another with reference to
                  these, but quickly changes, becoming cold instead of warm, ill instead of
                  well.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">So it is with all other dispositions also, unless through lapse
                  of time a disposition has itself become inveterate and almost impossible to
                  dislodge: in which case we should perhaps go so far as to call it a habit.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is evident that men incline to call those conditions habits
                  which are of a more or less permanent type and difficult to displace;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for those who are not retentive of knowledge, but volatile, are
                  not said to have such and such a 'habit' as regards knowledge, yet they are
                  disposed, we may say, either better or worse, towards knowledge.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Thus habit differs from disposition in this, that while the
                  latter in ephemeral, the former is permanent and difficult to alter.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Habits are at the same time dispositions, but dispositions are
                  not necessarily habits.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For those who have some specific habit may be said also, in
                  virtue of that habit, to be thus or thus disposed; but those who are disposed in
                  some specific way have not in all cases the corresponding habit.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="2">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Another sort of quality is that in virtue of which, for example,
                  we call men good boxers or runners, or healthy or sickly: in fact it includes all
                  those terms which refer to inborn capacity or incapacity.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Such things are not predicated of a person in virtue of his
                  disposition, but in virtue of his inborn capacity or incapacity to do something
                  with ease or to avoid defeat of any kind.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Persons are called good boxers or good runners, not in virtue of
                  such and such a disposition, but in virtue of an inborn capacity to accomplish
                  something with ease. Men are called healthy in virtue of the inborn capacity of
                  easy resistance to those unhealthy influences that may ordinarily arise;
                  unhealthy, in virtue of the lack of this capacity.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Similarly with regard to softness and hardness.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Hardness is predicated of a thing because it has that capacity
                  of resistance which enables it to withstand disintegration; softness, again, is
                  predicated of a thing by reason of the lack of that capacity.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="3">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">A third class within this category is that of affective
                  qualities and affections.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Sweetness, bitterness, sourness, are examples of this sort of
                  quality, together with all that is akin to these; heat, moreover, and cold,
                  whiteness, and blackness are affective qualities.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is evident that these are qualities,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for those things that possess them are themselves said to be
                  such and such by reason of their presence.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Honey is called sweet because it contains sweetness; the body is
                  called white because it contains whiteness;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">and so in all other cases.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The term 'affective quality' is not used as indicating that
                  those things which admit these qualities are affected in any way.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Honey is not called sweet because it is affected in a specific
                  way, nor is this what is meant in any other instance.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Similarly heat and cold are called affective qualities, not
                  because those things which admit them are affected. What is meant is that these
                  said qualities are capable of producing an 'affection' in the way of
                  perception.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">For sweetness has the power of affecting the sense of taste;
                  heat, that of touch; and so it is with the rest of these qualities.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Whiteness and blackness, however, and the other colours, are not
                  said to be affective qualities in this sense, but -because they themselves are the
                  results of an affection.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is plain that many changes of colour take place because of
                  affections.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">When a man is ashamed, he blushes; when he is afraid, he becomes
                  pale, and so on.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">So true is this, that when a man is by nature liable to such
                  affections, arising from some concomitance of elements in his constitution, it is
                  a probable inference that he has the corresponding complexion of skin.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">For the same disposition of bodily elements, which in the former
                  instance was momentarily present in the case of an access of shame, might be a
                  result of a man's natural temperament, so as to produce the corresponding
                  colouring also as a natural characteristic.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">All conditions, therefore, of this kind, if caused by certain
                  permanent and lasting affections, are called affective qualities.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For pallor and duskiness of complexion are called qualities,
                  inasmuch as we are said to be such and such in virtue of them, not only if they
                  originate in natural constitution, but also if they come about through long
                  disease or sunburn, and are difficult to remove, or indeed remain throughout life.
                  For in the same way we are said to be such and such because of these.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Those conditions, however, which arise from causes which may
                  easily be rendered ineffective or speedily removed, are called, not qualities, but
                  affections:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for we are not said to be such virtue of them.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">The man who blushes through shame is not said to be a
                  constitutional blusher, nor is the man who becomes pale through fear said to be
                  constitutionally pale. He is said rather to have been affected.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Thus such conditions are called affections, not qualities.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="8">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In like manner there are affective qualities and affections of
                  the soul.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="9">
               <div type="ic" n="1">That temper with which a man is born and which has its origin in
                  certain deep-seated affections is called a quality. I mean such conditions as
                  insanity, irascibility, and so on:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for people are said to be mad or irascible in virtue of
                  these.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="10">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Similarly those abnormal psychic states which are not inborn,
                  but arise from the concomitance of certain other elements, and are difficult to
                  remove, or altogether permanent, are called qualities,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for in virtue of them men are said to be such and such.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="11">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Those, however, which arise from causes easily rendered
                  ineffective are called affections, not qualities. Suppose that a man is irritable
                  when vexed:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">he is not even spoken of as a bad-tempered man, when in such
                  circumstances he loses his temper somewhat, but rather is said to be
                  affected.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Such conditions are therefore termed, not qualities, but
                  affections.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="4">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The fourth sort of quality is figure and the shape that belongs
                  to a thing; and besides this, straightness and curvedness and any other qualities
                  of this type;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">each of these defines a thing as being such and such.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Because it is triangular or quadrangular a thing is said to have
                  a specific character, or again because it is straight or curved;</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">in fact a thing's shape in every case gives rise to a
                  qualification of it.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Rarity and density, roughness and smoothness, seem to be terms
                  indicating quality: yet these, it would appear, really belong to a class different
                  from that of quality.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For it is rather a certain relative position of the parts
                  composing the thing thus qualified which, it appears, is indicated by each of
                  these terms.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">A thing is dense, owing to the fact that its parts are closely
                  combined with one another; rare, because there are interstices between the
                  parts;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">smooth, because its parts lie, so to speak, evenly; rough,
                  because some parts project beyond others.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">There may be other sorts of quality, but those that are most
                  properly so called have, we may safely say, been enumerated.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="5">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">These, then, are qualities, and the things that take their name
                  from them as derivatives, or are in some other way dependent on them, are said to
                  be qualified in some specific way.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In most, indeed in almost all cases, the name of that which is
                  qualified is derived from that of the quality. Thus the terms 'whiteness',
                  'grammar', 'justice', give us the adjectives 'white', 'grammatical', 'just', and
                  so on.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">There are some cases, however, in which, as the quality under
                  consideration has no name, it is impossible that those possessed of it should have
                  a name that is derivative.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For instance, the name given to the runner or boxer, who is so
                  called in virtue of an inborn capacity, is not derived from that of any
                  quality;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for lob those capacities have no name assigned to them. In this,
                  the inborn capacity is distinct from the science, with reference to which men are
                  called, e.g. boxers or wrestlers. Such a science is classed as a disposition; it
                  has a name, and is called 'boxing' or 'wrestling' as the case may be, and the name
                  given to those disposed in this way is derived from that of the science.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Sometimes, even though a name exists for the quality, that which
                  takes its character from the quality has a name that is not a derivative.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For instance, the upright man takes his character from the
                  possession of the quality of integrity, but the name given him is not derived from
                  the word 'integrity'.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Yet this does not occur often.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">We may therefore state that those things are said to be
                  possessed of some specific quality which have a name derived from that of the
                  aforesaid quality, or which are in some other way dependent on it.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="6">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">One quality may be the contrary of another; thus justice is the
                  contrary of injustice, whiteness of blackness, and so on. The things, also, which
                  are said to be such and such in virtue of these qualities, may be contrary the one
                  to the other; for that which is unjust is contrary to that which is just, that
                  which is white to that which is black.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">This, however, is not always the case.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Red, yellow, and such colours, though qualities, have no
                  contraries.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">If one of two contraries is a quality, the other will also be a
                  quality.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">This will be evident from particular instances, if we apply the
                  names used to denote the other categories; for instance, granted that justice is
                  the contrary of injustice and justice is a quality, injustice will also be a
                  quality:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">neither quantity, nor relation, nor place, nor indeed any other
                  category but that of quality, will be applicable properly to injustice.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">So it is with all other contraries falling under the category of
                  quality.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="9">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Qualities admit of variation of degree.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Whiteness is predicated of one thing in a greater or less degree
                  than of another. This is also the case with reference to justice.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Moreover, one and the same thing may exhibit a quality in a
                  greater degree than it did before: if a thing is white, it may become
                  whiter.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Though this is generally the case, there are exceptions.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">For if we should say that justice admitted of variation of
                  degree, difficulties might ensue, and this is true with regard to all those
                  qualities which are dispositions.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">There are some, indeed, who dispute the possibility of variation
                  here.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">They maintain that justice and health cannot very well admit of
                  variation of degree themselves, but that people vary in the degree in which they
                  possess these qualities, and that this is the case with grammatical learning and
                  all those qualities which are classed as dispositions.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">However that may be, it is an incontrovertible fact that the
                  things which in virtue of these qualities are said to be what they are vary in the
                  degree in which they possess them;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for one man is said to be better versed in grammar, or more
                  healthy or just, than another, and so on.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The qualities expressed by the terms 'triangular' and
                  'quadrangular' do not appear to admit of variation of degree, nor indeed do any
                  that have to do with figure.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For those things to which the definition of the triangle or
                  circle is applicable are all equally triangular or circular. Those, on the other
                  hand, to which the same definition is not applicable, cannot be said to differ
                  from one another in degree;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">the square is no more a circle than the rectangle,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">for to neither is the definition of the circle
                  appropriate.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In short, if the definition of the term proposed is not
                  applicable to both objects, they cannot be compared.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Thus it is not all qualities which admit of variation of
                  degree.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="2">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Whereas none of the characteristics I have mentioned are
                  peculiar to quality, the fact that likeness and unlikeness can be predicated with
                  reference to quality only, gives to that category its distinctive feature.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">One thing is like another only with reference to that in virtue
                  of which it is such and such;</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">thus this forms the peculiar mark of quality.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="3">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">We must not be disturbed because it may be argued that, though
                  proposing to discuss the category of quality, we have included in it many relative
                  terms.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">We did say that habits and dispositions were relative.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In practically all such cases the genus is relative, the
                  individual not.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Thus knowledge, as a genus, is explained by reference to
                  something else, for we mean a knowledge of something.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">But particular branches of knowledge are not thus explained. The
                  knowledge of grammar is not relative to anything external, nor is the knowledge of
                  music, but these, if relative at all, are relative only in virtue of their
                  genera;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">thus grammar is said be the knowledge of something, not the
                  grammar of something; similarly music is the knowledge of something, not the music
                  of something.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Thus individual branches of knowledge are not relative.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">And it is because we possess these individual branches of
                  knowledge that we are said to be such and such.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">It is these that we actually possess: we are called experts
                  because we possess knowledge in some particular branch.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Those particular branches, therefore, of knowledge, in virtue of
                  which we are sometimes said to be such and such,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">are themselves qualities, and are not relative.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Further, if anything should happen to fall within both the
                  category of quality and that of relation, there would be nothing extraordinary in
                  classing it under both these heads.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="5">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Action and affection both admit of contraries and also of
                  variation of degree.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Heating is the contrary of cooling, being heated of being
                  cooled, being glad of being vexed.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Thus they admit of contraries.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">They also admit of variation of degree:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for it is possible to heat in a greater or less degree; also to
                  be heated in a greater or less degree.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Thus action and affection also admit of variation of
                  degree.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="7">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">So much, then, is stated with regard to these categories.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">We spoke, moreover, of the category of position when we were
                  dealing with that of relation, and stated that such terms derived their names from
                  those of the corresponding attitudes.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">As for the rest, time, place, state, since they are easily
                  intelligible, I say no more about them than was said at the beginning, that in the
                  category of state are included such states as 'shod', 'armed', in that of place
                  'in the Lyceum' and so on, as was explained before.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The proposed categories have, then, been adequately dealt
                  with.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">We must next explain the various senses in which the term
                  'opposite' is used.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="10">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Things are said to be opposed in four senses: (i) as
                  correlatives to one another, (ii) as contraries to one another, (iii) as
                  privatives to positives, (iv) as affirmatives to negatives.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Let me sketch my meaning in outline. An instance of the use of
                  the word 'opposite' with reference to correlatives is afforded by the expressions
                  'double' and 'half'; with reference to contraries by 'bad' and 'good'. Opposites
                  in the sense of 'privatives' and 'positives' are' blindness' and 'sight'; in the
                  sense of affirmatives and negatives, the propositions 'he sits', 'he does not
                  sit'.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="2">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">(i) Pairs of opposites which fall under the category of relation
                  are explained by a reference of the one to the other, the reference being
                  indicated by the preposition 'of' or by some other preposition.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Thus, double is a relative term, for that which is double is
                  explained as the double of something.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Knowledge, again, is the opposite of the thing known, in the
                  same sense;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">and the thing known also is explained by its relation to its
                  opposite, knowledge.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">For the thing known is explained as that which is known by
                  something, that is, by knowledge.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="3">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Such things, then, as are opposite the one to the other in the
                  sense of being correlatives are explained by a reference of the one to the
                  other.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">(ii) Pairs of opposites which are contraries are not in any way
                  interdependent, but are contrary the one to the other.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">The good is not spoken of as the good of the had, but as the
                  contrary of the bad, nor is white spoken of as the white of the black, but as the
                  contrary of the black.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">These two types of opposition are therefore distinct.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Those contraries which are such that the subjects in which they
                  are naturally present, or of which they are predicated, must necessarily contain
                  either the one or the other of them, have no intermediate,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">but those in the case of which no such necessity obtains, always
                  have an intermediate.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Thus disease and health are naturally present in the body of an
                  animal, and it is necessary that either the one or the other should be present in
                  the body of an animal.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Odd and even, again, are predicated of number, and it is
                  necessary that the one or the other should be present in numbers.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Now there is no intermediate between the terms of either of
                  these two pairs.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">On the other hand, in those contraries with regard to which no
                  such necessity obtains, we find an intermediate.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Blackness and whiteness are naturally present in the body, but
                  it is not necessary that either the one or the other should be present in the
                  body, inasmuch as it is not true to say that everybody must be white or
                  black.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Badness and goodness, again, are predicated of man, and of many
                  other things, but it is not necessary that either the one quality or the other
                  should be present in that of which they are predicated:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">it is not true to say that everything that may be good or bad
                  must be either good or bad.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">These pairs of contraries have intermediates: the intermediates
                  between white and black are grey, sallow, and all the other colours that come
                  between; the intermediate between good and bad is that which is neither the one
                  nor the other.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Some intermediate qualities have names, such as grey and sallow
                  and all the other colours that come between white and black;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">in other cases, however, it is not easy to name the
                  intermediate, but we must define it as that which is not either extreme, as in the
                  case of that which is neither good nor bad, neither just nor unjust.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="4">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">(iii) 'privatives' and 'Positives' have reference to the same
                  subject. Thus, sight and blindness have reference to the eye.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">It is a universal rule that each of a pair of opposites of this
                  type has reference to that to which the particular 'positive' is natural.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">We say that that is capable of some particular faculty or
                  possession has suffered privation when the faculty or possession in question is in
                  no way present in that in which, and at the time at which, it should naturally be
                  present.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">We do not call that toothless which has not teeth, or that blind
                  which has not sight, but rather that which has not teeth or sight at the time when
                  by nature it should.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">For there are some creatures which from birth are without sight,
                  or without teeth, but these are not called toothless or blind.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">To be without some faculty or to possess it is not the same as
                  the corresponding 'privative' or 'positive'.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">'Sight' is a 'positive', 'blindness' a 'privative', but 'to
                  possess sight' is not equivalent to 'sight', 'to be blind' is not equivalent to
                  'blindness'.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Blindness is a 'privative', to be blind is to be in a state of
                  privation, but is not a 'privative'.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Moreover, if 'blindness' were equivalent to 'being blind', both
                  would be predicated of the same subject;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">but though a man is said to be blind, he is by no means said to
                  be blindness.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">To be in a state of 'possession' is, it appears, the opposite of
                  being in a state of 'privation', just as 'positives' and 'privatives' themselves
                  are opposite.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">There is the same type of antithesis in both cases;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for just as blindness is opposed to sight, so is being blind
                  opposed to having sight.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">That which is affirmed or denied is not itself affirmation or
                  denial.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">By 'affirmation' we mean an affirmative proposition, by 'denial'
                  a negative. Now, those facts which form the matter of the affirmation or denial
                  are not propositions;</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="7">
               <div type="ic" n="1">yet these two are said to be opposed in the same sense as the
                  affirmation and denial, for in this case also the type of antithesis is the
                  same.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For as the affirmation is opposed to the denial, as in the two
                  propositions 'he sits', 'he does not sit',</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">so also the fact which constitutes the matter of the proposition
                  in one case is opposed to that in the other, his sitting, that is to say, to his
                  not sitting.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="8">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is evident that 'positives' and 'privatives' are not opposed
                  each to each in the same sense as relatives.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">The one is not explained by reference to the other;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">sight is not sight of blindness, nor is any other preposition
                  used to indicate the relation.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Similarly blindness is not said to be blindness of sight, but
                  rather, privation of sight.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="9">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Relatives, moreover, reciprocate; if blindness, therefore, were
                  a relative, there would be a reciprocity of relation between it and that with
                  which it was correlative.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">But this is not the case.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Sight is not called the sight of blindness.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="5">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">That those terms which fall under the heads of 'positives' and
                  'privatives' are not opposed each to each as contraries, either, is plain from the
                  following facts:</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Of a pair of contraries such that they have no intermediate, one
                  or the other must needs be present in the subject in which they naturally subsist,
                  or of which they are predicated;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for it is those, as we proved,' in the case of which this
                  necessity obtains, that have no intermediate. Moreover, we cited health and
                  disease, odd and even, as instances.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">But those contraries which have an intermediate are not subject
                  to any such necessity.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">It is not necessary that every substance, receptive of such
                  qualities, should be either black or white, cold or hot, for something
                  intermediate between these contraries may very well be present in the
                  subject.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">We proved, moreover, that those contraries have an intermediate
                  in the case of which the said necessity does not obtain. Yet when one of the two
                  contraries is a constitutive property of the subject, as it is a constitutive
                  property of fire to be hot, of snow to be white,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">it is necessary determinately that one of the two contraries,
                  not one or the other, should be present in the subject;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="7">for fire cannot be cold, or snow black.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="8">Thus, it is not the case here that one of the two must needs be
                  present in every subject receptive of these qualities, but only in that subject of
                  which the one forms a constitutive property. Moreover, in such cases it is one
                  member of the pair determinately, and not either the one or the other, which must
                  be present.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In the case of 'positives' and 'privatives', on the other hand,
                  neither of the aforesaid statements holds good.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For it is not necessary that a subject receptive of the
                  qualities should always have either the one or the other; that which has not yet
                  advanced to the state when sight is natural is not said either to be blind or to
                  see. Thus 'positives' and 'privatives' do not belong to that class of contraries
                  which consists of those which have no intermediate.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">On the other hand, they do not belong either to that class which
                  consists of contraries which have an intermediate.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">For under certain conditions it is necessary that either the one
                  or the other should form part of the constitution of every appropriate
                  subject.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">For when a thing has reached the stage when it is by nature
                  capable of sight, it will be said either to see or to be blind, and that in an
                  indeterminate sense, signifying that the capacity may be either present or absent;
                  for it is not necessary either that it should see or that it should be blind, but
                  that it should be either in the one state or in the other.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">Yet in the case of those contraries which have an intermediate
                  we found that it was never necessary that either the one or the other should be
                  present in every appropriate subject, but only that in certain subjects one of the
                  pair should be present, and that in a determinate sense.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is, therefore, plain that 'positives' and 'privatives' are
                  not opposed each to each in either of the senses in which contraries are
                  opposed.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Again, in the case of contraries, it is possible that there
                  should be changes from either into the other, while the subject retains its
                  identity, unless indeed one of the contraries is a constitutive property of that
                  subject, as heat is of fire.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For it is possible that that that which is healthy should become
                  diseased, that which is white, black, that which is cold, hot, that which is good,
                  bad, that which is bad, good.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">The bad man, if he is being brought into a better way of life
                  and thought, may make some advance, however slight,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">and if he should once improve, even ever so little, it is plain
                  that he might change completely, or at any rate make very great progress;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">for a man becomes more and more easily moved to virtue, however
                  small the improvement was at first. It is, therefore, natural to suppose that he
                  will make yet greater progress than he has made in the past;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">and as this process goes on, it will change him completely and
                  establish him in the contrary state, provided he is not hindered by lack of
                  time.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="7">In the case of 'positives' and 'privatives', however, change in
                  both directions is impossible.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="8">There may be a change from possession to privation, but not from
                  privation to possession.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="9">The man who has become blind does not regain his sight; the man
                  who has become bald does not regain his hair; the man who has lost his teeth does
                  not grow his grow a new set.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="6">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">(iv) Statements opposed as affirmation and negation belong
                  manifestly to a class which is distinct,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for in this case, and in this case only, it is necessary for the
                  one opposite to be true and the other false.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Neither in the case of contraries, nor in the case of
                  correlatives, nor in the case of 'positives' and 'privatives', is it necessary for
                  one to be true and the other false.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Health and disease are contraries: neither of them is true or
                  false.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">'Double' and 'half' are opposed to each other as correlatives:
                  neither of them is true or false.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">The case is the same, of course, with regard to 'positives' and
                  'privatives' such as 'sight' and 'blindness'.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">In short, where there is no sort of combination of words, truth
                  and falsity have no place,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">and all the opposites we have mentioned so far consist of simple
                  words.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">At the same time, when the words which enter into opposed
                  statements are contraries, these, more than any other set of opposites, would seem
                  to claim this characteristic. 'Socrates is ill' is the contrary of 'Socrates is
                  well', but not even of such composite expressions is it true to say that one of
                  the pair must always be true and the other false.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For if Socrates exists, one will be true and the other false,
                  but if he does not exist, both will be false;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for neither 'Socrates is ill' nor 'Socrates is well' is true, if
                  Socrates does not exist at all.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In the case of 'positives' and 'privatives', if the subject does
                  not exist at all, neither proposition is true, but even if the subject exists, it
                  is not always the fact that one is true and the other false.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For 'Socrates has sight' is the opposite of 'Socrates is blind'
                  in the sense of the word 'opposite' which applies to possession and privation. Now
                  if Socrates exists, it is not necessary that one should be true and the other
                  false, for when he is not yet able to acquire the power of vision, both are false,
                  as also if Socrates is altogether non-existent.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">But in the case of affirmation and negation, whether the subject
                  exists or not, one is always false and the other true.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For manifestly, if Socrates exists, one of the two propositions
                  'Socrates is ill', 'Socrates is not ill', is true, and the other false.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">This is likewise the case if he does not exist; for if he does
                  not exist, to say that he is ill is false, to say that he is not ill is
                  true.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Thus it is in the case of those opposites only, which are
                  opposite in the sense in which the term is used with reference to affirmation and
                  negation, that the rule holds good, that one of the pair must be true and the
                  other false.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="11">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">That the contrary of a good is an evil is shown by induction:
                  the contrary of health is disease, of courage, cowardice, and so on. But the
                  contrary of an evil is sometimes a good, sometimes an evil.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For defect, which is an evil, has excess for its contrary, this
                  also being an evil,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">and the mean, which is a good, is equally the contrary of the
                  one and of the other.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is only in a few cases, however, that we see instances of
                  this: in most, the contrary of an evil is a good.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In the case of contraries, it is not always necessary that if
                  one exists the other should also exist:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for if all become healthy there will be health and no
                  disease,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">and again, if everything turns white, there will be white, but
                  no black.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Again, since the fact that Socrates is ill is the contrary of
                  the fact that Socrates is well, and two contrary conditions cannot both obtain in
                  one and the same individual at the same time, both these contraries could not
                  exist at once: for if that</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Socrates was well was a fact, then that Socrates was ill could
                  not possibly be one.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="2">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is plain that contrary attributes must needs be present in
                  subjects which belong to the same species or genus.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Disease and health require as their subject the body of an
                  animal; white and black require a body, without further qualification; justice and
                  injustice require as their subject the human soul.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Moreover, it is necessary that pairs of contraries should in all
                  cases either belong to the same genus or belong to contrary genera or be
                  themselves genera.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">White and black belong to the same genus, colour; justice and
                  injustice, to contrary genera, virtue and vice; while good and evil do not belong
                  to genera, but are themselves actual genera, with terms under them.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="12">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">There are four senses in which one thing can be said to be
                  'prior' to another.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Primarily and most properly the term has reference to time: in
                  this sense the word is used to indicate that one thing is older or more ancient
                  than another, for the expressions 'older' and 'more ancient' imply greater length
                  of time.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Secondly, one thing is said to be 'prior' to another when the
                  sequence of their being cannot be reversed.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">In this sense 'one' is 'prior' to 'two'. For if 'two' exists, it
                  follows directly that 'one' must exist, but if 'one' exists, it does not follow
                  necessarily that 'two' exists: thus the sequence subsisting cannot be reversed. It
                  is agreed, then, that when the sequence of two things cannot be reversed, then
                  that one on which the other depends is called 'prior' to that other.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In the third place, the term 'prior' is used with reference to
                  any order, as in the case of science and of oratory.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For in sciences which use demonstration there is that which is
                  prior and that which is posterior in order; in geometry, the elements are prior to
                  the propositions; in reading and writing, the letters of the alphabet are prior to
                  the syllables. Similarly, in the case of speeches, the exordium is prior in order
                  to the narrative.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Besides these senses of the word, there is a fourth. That which
                  is better and more honourable is said to have a natural priority.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">In common parlance men speak of those whom they honour and love
                  as 'coming first' with them.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">This sense of the word is perhaps the most far-fetched.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="2">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Such, then, are the different senses in which the term 'prior'
                  is used.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Yet it would seem that besides those mentioned there is yet
                  another.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For in those things, the being of each of which implies that of
                  the other, that which is in any way the cause may reasonably be said to be by
                  nature 'prior' to the effect.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is plain that there are instances of this.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">The fact of the being of a man carries with it the truth of the
                  proposition that he is, and the implication is reciprocal:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for if a man is, the proposition wherein we allege that he is
                  true,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">and conversely, if the proposition wherein we allege that he is
                  true, then he is.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">The true proposition, however, is in no way the cause of the
                  being of the man, but the fact of the man's being does seem somehow to be the
                  cause of the truth of the proposition,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">for the truth or falsity of the proposition depends on the fact
                  of the man's being or not being.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Thus the word 'prior' may be used in five senses.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="13">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The term 'simultaneous' is primarily and most appropriately
                  applied to those things the genesis of the one of which is simultaneous with that
                  of the other;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for in such cases neither is prior or posterior to the
                  other.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Such things are said to be simultaneous in point of time.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Those things, again, are 'simultaneous' in point of nature, the
                  being of each of which involves that of the other, while at the same time neither
                  is the cause of the other's being.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">This is the case with regard to the double and the half, for
                  these are reciprocally dependent, since, if there is a double, there is also a
                  half, and if there is a half, there is also a double, while at the same time
                  neither is the cause of the being of the other.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Again, those species which are distinguished one from another
                  and opposed one to another within the same genus are said to be 'simultaneous' in
                  nature.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">I mean those species which are distinguished each from each by
                  one and the same method of division. Thus the 'winged' species is simultaneous
                  with the 'terrestrial' and the 'water' species.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">These are distinguished within the same genus, and are opposed
                  each to each,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for the genus 'animal' has the 'winged', the 'terrestrial', and
                  the 'water' species, and no one of these is prior or posterior to another; on the
                  contrary, all such things appear to be 'simultaneous' in nature.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">Each of these also, the terrestrial, the winged, and the water
                  species, can be divided again into subspecies.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Those species, then, also will be 'simultaneous' point of
                  nature, which, belonging to the same genus, are distinguished each from each by
                  one and the same method of differentiation.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">But genera are prior to species,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for the sequence of their being cannot be reversed.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">If there is the species 'water-animal', there will be the genus
                  'animal', but granted the being of the genus 'animal', it does not follow
                  necessarily that there will be the species 'water-animal'.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="6">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Those things, therefore, are said to be 'simultaneous' in
                  nature, the being of each of which involves that of the other, while at the same
                  time neither is in any way the cause of the other's being; those species, also,
                  which are distinguished each from each and opposed within the same genus.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Those things, moreover, are 'simultaneous' in the unqualified
                  sense of the word which come into being at the same time.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="14">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">There are six sorts of movement:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">generation, destruction, increase, diminution, alteration, and
                  change of place.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">It is evident in all but one case that all these sorts of
                  movement are distinct each from each.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">Generation is distinct from destruction, increase and change of
                  place from diminution, and so on.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">But in the case of alteration it may be argued that the process
                  necessarily implies one or other of the other five sorts of motion.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">This is not true,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">for we may say that all affections, or nearly all, produce in us
                  an alteration which is distinct from all other sorts of motion,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for that which is affected need not suffer either increase or
                  diminution or any of the other sorts of motion. Thus alteration is a distinct sort
                  of motion;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">for, if it were not, the thing altered would not only be
                  altered, but would forthwith necessarily suffer increase or diminution or some one
                  of the other sorts of motion in addition;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">which as a matter of fact is not the case.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="4">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Similarly that which was undergoing the process of increase or
                  was subject to some other sort of motion would, if alteration were not a distinct
                  form of motion, necessarily be subject to alteration also.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">But there are some things which undergo increase but yet not
                  alteration.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">The square, for instance, if a gnomon is applied to it,
                  undergoes increase but not alteration,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">and so it is with all other figures of this sort.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="5">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Alteration and increase, therefore, are distinct.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="par" n="2">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Speaking generally, rest is the contrary of motion.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">But the different forms of motion have their own contraries in
                  other forms; thus destruction is the contrary of generation, diminution of
                  increase,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">rest in a place, of change of place. As for this last, change in
                  the reverse direction would seem to be most truly its contrary; thus motion
                  upwards is the contrary of motion downwards and vice versa.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">In the case of that sort of motion which yet remains, of those
                  that have been enumerated, it is not easy to state what is its contrary. It
                  appears to have no contrary, unless one should define the contrary here also
                  either as 'rest in its quality' or as 'change in the direction of the contrary
                  quality', just as we defined the contrary of change of place either as rest in a
                  place or as change in the reverse direction.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">For a thing is altered when change of quality takes place;
                  therefore either rest in its quality or change in the direction of the contrary
                  may be called the contrary of this qualitative form of motion. In this way
                  becoming white is the contrary of becoming black;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">there is alteration in the contrary direction, since a change of
                  a qualitative nature takes place.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ch" n="15">
         <div type="par" n="1">
            <div type="s" n="1">
               <div type="ic" n="1">The term 'to have' is used in various senses.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">In the first place it is used with reference to habit or
                  disposition or any other quality, for we are said to 'have' a piece of knowledge
                  or a virtue.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">Then, again, it has reference to quantity, as, for instance, in
                  the case of a man's height; for he is said to 'have' a height of three or four
                  cubits.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="4">It is used, moreover, with regard to apparel, a man being said
                  to 'have' a coat or tunic;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="5">or in respect of something which we have on a part of ourselves,
                  as a ring on the hand:</div>
               <div type="ic" n="6">or in respect of something which is a part of us, as hand or
                  foot.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="7">The term refers also to content, as in the case of a vessel and
                  wheat, or of a jar and wine; a jar is said to 'have' wine, and a corn-measure
                  wheat.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="8">The expression in such cases has reference to content.</div>
               <div type="ic" n="9">Or it refers to that which has been acquired;</div>
               <div type="ic" n="10">we are said to 'have' a house or a field.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="2">
               <div type="ic" n="1">A man is also said to 'have' a wife, and a wife a husband,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="2">and this appears to be the most remote meaning of the
                  term,</div>
               <div type="ic" n="3">for by the use of it we mean simply that the husband lives with
                  the wife.</div>
            </div>
            <div type="s" n="3">
               <div type="ic" n="1">Other senses of the word might perhaps be found, but the most
                  ordinary ones have all been enumerated.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
   </body>
</TAN-T>