<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/TAN-TEI.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/TAN.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" 
   xmlns:tan="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns" xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" 
   xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" TAN-version="2021" 
   id="tag:parkj@textalign.net,2015:patricius.confession.2003.eng">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Confession of St Patrick</title>
            <title type="sub">A digital edition of the English translation by Pádraig
               McCarthy</title>
            <author>
               <persName instant="false" full="yes">Patrick</persName> (<persName type="latin" instant="false" full="yes">Patricius</persName>, <persName type="old-irish" instant="false" full="yes">Pátraic</persName>, <persName type="irish" instant="false" full="yes">Pádraig</persName>)
                  <date instant="false">(c.420–490?)</date>
               <roleName full="yes">Bishop</roleName>, <roleName full="yes">Patron Saint of Ireland</roleName>
            </author>
            <author>
               <persName instant="false" full="yes">Pádraig McCarthy</persName>
               <roleName full="yes">Translator</roleName>
            </author>
            <editor>The Saint Patrick's Confessio Hypertext Stack Project</editor>
            <principal>
               <name full="yes" instant="false">
                  <persName instant="false" full="yes">Anthony Harvey</persName>
                  <roleName full="yes">Project Leader</roleName>
                  <orgName instant="false" full="yes">Royal Irish Academy</orgName>
               </name>
            </principal>
            <editor>
               <name full="yes" instant="false">
                  <persName instant="false" full="yes">Franz Fischer</persName>
                  <roleName full="yes">Postdoctoral Researcher</roleName>
                  <orgName instant="false" full="yes">Royal Irish Academy</orgName>
               </name>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Translation from Latin by</resp>
               <persName instant="false" full="yes">Pádraig McCarthy</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Project Leader</resp>
               <persName instant="false" full="yes">Anthony Harvey</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Project Researcher</resp>
               <name full="yes" instant="false">
                  <persName instant="false" full="yes">Franz Fischer</persName>
                  <roleName full="yes">Principal Researcher</roleName>
               </name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Project Interns</resp>
               <name full="yes" instant="false">
                  <persName instant="false" full="yes">Roman Bleier</persName>
                  <roleName full="yes">Erasmus Postgrad Intern 2011</roleName>
               </name>
               <name full="yes" instant="false">
                  <persName instant="false" full="yes">Alessio Frenda</persName>
                  <roleName full="yes">Summer Postgrad Intern 2010</roleName>
               </name>
               <name full="yes" instant="false">
                  <persName instant="false" full="yes">Daniela Schulz</persName>
                  <roleName full="yes">Summer Postgrad Intern 2011</roleName>
               </name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Structural Markup Transformation</resp>
               <name full="yes" instant="false">
                  <persName instant="false" full="yes">Randall Cream</persName>
                  <orgName instant="false" full="yes">Digital Humanities Observatory</orgName>
                  <orgName instant="false" full="yes">Royal Irish Academy</orgName>
               </name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p part="N">The Stack gathers high resolution scans of all extant manuscript testimonies and – in
               the form of a meta-edition – reproductions of relevant editions that have been
               published: From the editio princeps, that is the first ever printed version of the
               Confessio – edited by Sir James Ware in 1656 and based on the Irish and British
               manuscript copies only – up to the canonical version of the critical text established
               in the scholarly edition by Ludwig Bieler in 1950.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p part="N">The Saint Patrick’s Confessio Hypertext Stack Project is funded under the Irish
               government Programme for Research in Third-Level Institutions (PRTLI), Cycle 4. It is
               part of the Humanities Serving Irish Society (HSIS) initiative, a partnership of
               equals committed to developing an inter-institutional research infrastructure for the
               humanities. The Hyperstack is one of two projects running at Royal Irish Academy
               under the label ADR, "Academy Digital Resources", supported by the Digital Humanities
               Observatory (DHO). (The second ADR project being the Doegen Project building up a
               digital archive of Irish dialect recordings).</p>
            <p part="N">The Hyperstack Project was conceived and is overseen by Dr Anthony Harvey, editor of
               the Royal Irish Academy Dictionary of Medieval Latin from Celtic Sources. Since
               September 2008 Dr Franz Fischer has been the postdoctoral researcher in charge. A
               series of collaborators facilitate the project and greatly enhance its value. Not
               least there is a postgrad intern for three months each summer.</p>
            <p part="N">The St Patrick’s Confessio Hypertext Stack Project aims to give Irish society as
               direct access as possible to the historical Patrick. In order to achieve this the
               project aims to build up a comprehensive digital research environment to make
               accessible to academic specialists, as well as to interested lay people, all the
               textual aspects of the real St Patrick’s own work.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc default="false">
            <bibl default="false" status="draft">
               <title type="main">My Name is Patrick</title>
               <title type="subtitle">The Confessio of St Patrick and his Letter to the Soldiers of
                  Coroticus</title>
               <author>
                  <persName instant="false" full="yes">Patrick</persName>
                  <date instant="false">(c.420–490?)</date>
                  <roleName full="yes">Bishop</roleName>, <roleName full="yes">Patron Saint of Ireland</roleName></author>
               <author>
                  <persName instant="false" full="yes">Pádraig McCarthy</persName>
                  <roleName full="yes">Translator</roleName>
                  <placeName instant="false" full="yes">St John the Baptist parish, Blackrock, Co. Dublin</placeName>
               </author>
               <note type="rights" anchored="true">
                  <persName instant="false" full="yes">Pádraig McCarthy</persName>
                  <date instant="false">© 2003</date>
                  <quote defective="false">You are encouraged to copy this freely, as long as you include the
                     copyright notice as on the front. Please look only to cover the costs you
                     incur. </quote>
               </note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p part="N">All electronic text versions of St Patrick's Confessio and his his Letter to the
            Soldiers of Coroticus are structured in correspondence to the original Latin as
            established by <ref type="biblio" cRef="White1905">N.J. White in his print edition from
               1905</ref> and as maintained in the <ref type="biblio" cRef="Bieler1950-1951">'canonical edition' by L. Bieler in 1950</ref> in order to align the original with
            the translations paragraph by paragraph. Bibliographical references refer to the
            HyperStack bibliography. </p>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <head xmlns="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns">
      <name>The Confession of St Patrick: A digital edition of the English translation by Pádraig
         McCarthy</name>
      <master-location href="http://textalign.net/release/TAN-2020/examples/patricius.confessio.2003.eng.xml"/>
      <license licensor="park">
         <IRI>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en_US</IRI>
         <name>This data file is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
            License. The license is granted independent of rights and licenses associated with the
            source. </name>
      </license>
      <reference-system type="logical" wf-ready="false"/>
      <work>
         <IRI>tag:parkj@textalign.net,2015:work:patricius:confessio</IRI>
         <name>Confession of St. Patrick</name>
      </work>
      <source>
         <IRI>tag:parkj@textalign.net,2015:source:http://www.confessio.ie/sites/confessio.ie/files/downloads/confessio_english.xml</IRI>
         <name>The Saint Patrick's Confessio Hypertext Stack Project edition</name>
         <checksum>
            <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Sha-1</IRI>
            <name>SHA-1</name>
            <value>91D95564ABDF2B2C1B9EEF016CBA51E8179646CC</value>
         </checksum>
         <location href="http://www.confessio.ie/sites/confessio.ie/files/downloads/confessio_english.xml" accessed-when="2015-01-25"/>
      </source>
      <adjustments>
         <normalization>
            <IRI>tag:textalign.net,2015:normalization:annotation-content-removed</IRI>
            <name>Footnotes or endnotes have been deleted.</name>
         </normalization>
      </adjustments>
      <vocabulary-key>
         <algorithm xml:id="xslt2">
            <IRI>tag:textalign.net,2015:stylesheet:convert-tan2018-to-tan2020</IRI>
            <name>Stylesheet to create a TAN file.</name>
            <location href="../applications/convert/convert%20TAN%202018%20to%20TAN%202020.xsl" accessed-when="2018-08-09T11:14:11.796-04:00"/>
         </algorithm>
         <div-type xml:id="sect" which="section"/>
         <div-type xml:id="para" which="paragraph"/><comment when="2016-01-25-05:00" who="park">The following agents and roles apply only to the
         preparation of the TAN file, not the original TEI file that serves as the source. See the
         teiHeader for details on responsibility.</comment>
         <person xml:id="park">
            <IRI>tag:parkj@textalign.net,2015:self</IRI>
            <name xml:lang="eng">Jenny Park</name>
         </person>
         <algorithm xml:id="xslt1"><IRI>tag:textalign.net,2015:stylesheet:convert-tan2017-to-tan2018</IRI><name>Stylesheet to populate a TAN-A file from collections.</name><location accessed-when="2018-08-09T11:14:11.796-04:00" href="../applications/convert/convert%20TAN%202017%20to%20TAN%202018.xsl"/></algorithm>
         <role xml:id="editor">
            <IRI>http://schema.org/editor</IRI>
            <name xml:lang="eng">Editor</name>
         </role>
         <role xml:id="stylesheet1" which="stylesheet"/>
      </vocabulary-key>
      
      <file-resp who="park"/>
      <resp who="xslt2" roles="stylesheet1"/>
      <resp roles="editor" who="park"/>
      <resp who="xslt1" roles="stylesheet1"/>
      
      <change when="2017-05-15" who="park">Normalized @n</change>
      <change when="2016-01-25" who="park">Created new TAN-TEI file.</change>
      <change who="xslt1" when="2017-11-02T22:26:38.519-04:00">TAN file updated to 2018 schemas.</change>
      <change who="xslt2" when="2018-08-09T11:14:11.796-04:00">Converted from 2018 to 2019 schemas.</change>
      <to-do>
         <comment when="2018-08-09-04:00" who="park">File needs to be checked.</comment>
      </to-do>
   </head>
   <text>
      <body xml:lang="eng">
         <div type="title" n="title" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><head>
            <title>The Confession of St Patrick</title>
         </head></div>
         <div xml:id="C01_eng" n="1" part="I" corresp="C01_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">My name is Patrick. I am a sinner, a simple country person, and the least of all
               believers. I am looked down upon by many.</p></div>
            <div type="para" n="2" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">My father was Calpornius. He was a deacon; his father was Potitus, a priest, who
               lived at Bannavem Taburniae. His home
               was near there, and that is where I was taken prisoner. I was about sixteen at the
               time.</p></div>
            <div type="para" n="3" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">At that time, I did not know the true God. I was taken into captivity in Ireland,
               along with thousands of others. We deserved this, because we had gone away from God,
               and did not keep his commandments. We would not listen to our priests, who advised us
               about how we could be saved. The Lord brought his strong anger upon us, and scattered us
               among many nations even to the ends of the earth. It was among foreigners that it was
               seen how little I was. </p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C02_eng" n="2" part="F" corresp="C02_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">It was there that the Lord opened up my awareness of my lack of faith. Even though it
               came about late, I recognised my failings. So I turned with all my heart to the Lord
               my God, and he looked down on my lowliness and had mercy on my youthful ignorance. He
               guarded me before I knew him, and before I came to wisdom and could distinguish
               between good and evil. He protected me and consoled me as a father does for his
               son.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C03_eng" n="3" corresp="C03_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">That is why I cannot be silent – nor would it be good to do so – about such great
               blessings and such a gift that the Lord so kindly bestowed in the land of my
               captivity. This is how we can repay such blessings, when our lives change and we come
               to know God, to praise and bear witness to his great wonders before every nation
               under heaven.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C04_eng" n="4" corresp="C04_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">This is because there is no other God, nor will there ever be, nor was there ever,
               except God the Father. He is the one who was not begotten, the one without a
               beginning, the one from whom all beginnings come, the one who holds all things in
               being – this is our teaching.</p></div>
            <div type="para" n="2" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">And his son, Jesus Christ, whom we testify has always been, since before the
               beginning of this age, with the father in a spiritual way. He was begotten in an
               indescribable way before every beginning. Everything we can see, and everything
               beyond our sight, was made through him. He became a human being; and, having overcome
               death, was welcomed to the heavens to the Father. The Father gave him all power over
               every being, both heavenly and earthly and beneath the earth. Let every tongue
               confess that Jesus Christ, in whom we believe and whom we await to come back to us in
               the near future, is Lord and God. He is judge of the living and of the dead; he rewards every person
               according to their deeds. He has generously poured on us the Holy
                  Spirit, the gift and promise of
               immortality, who makes believers and those who listen to be children of God and
               co-heirs with Christ. This is the one we
               acknowledge and adore – one God in a trinity of the sacred name.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C05_eng" n="5" corresp="C05_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">He said through the prophet: ‘Call on me in the day of your distress, and I will set
               you free, and you will glorify me.’
               Again he said: ‘It is a matter of honour to reveal and tell forth the works of
                  God.’</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C06_eng" n="6" corresp="C06_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">Although I am imperfect in many ways, I want my brothers and relations to know what
               I’m really like, so that they can see what it is that inspires my life.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C07_eng" n="7" corresp="C07_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">I am not ignoring the evidence of my Lord, who testifies in the psalm: ‘You destroy
               those who speak lies.’ And again he says: ‘A mouth which lies kills the soul.’
               And the same Lord says in the gospel: ‘The idle words which people speak, they will
               account for on the day of judgment.’</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C08_eng" n="8" corresp="C08_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">So I should greatly dread, with fear and trembling, this sentence on that day, where
               nobody can avoid or escape, but all shall give complete account of the least of sins
               before the tribunal of the Lord Christ.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C09_eng" n="9" corresp="C09_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">This is why I have long thought to write, but up to now I have hesitated, because I
               feared what people would say. This is because I did not learn as others did, who
               drank in equally well both the law and the sacred writings, and never had to change
               their way of speaking since childhood, but always grew better and better at it. For
               me, however, my speech and words have been translated into a foreign language, as it
               can be easily seen from my writings the standard of the instruction and learning I
               have had. As it is said: ‘The wise person is known through speech, and also
               understanding and knowledge and the teaching of truth.’</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C10_eng" n="10" corresp="C10_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">However, even though there’s truth in my excuse, it gets me nowhere. Now, in my old
               age, I want to do what I was unable to do in my youth. My sins then prevented me from
               really taking in what I read. But who believes me, even were I to repeat what I said
               previously? I was taken prisoner as a youth, particularly young in the matter of
               being able to speak, and before I knew what I should seek and what I should avoid.
               That is why, today, I blush and am afraid to expose my lack of experience, because I
               can’t express myself with the brief words I would like in my heart and soul.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C11_eng" n="11" corresp="C11_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">If I had been given the same chance as other people, I would not be silent, whatever
               the reward. If I seem to some to be too forward, with my lack of knowledge and my
               even slower tongue, still it is written: ‘Stammering tongues will quickly learn to
               speak peace.’ How much more should we want to do
               this, who are, as it is said, a saving letter of Christ even to the ends of the
               earth. Although it is not well expressed, still this letter is genuinely and strongly
               written in your hearts, not with ink, but with the spirit of the living God. The Spirit is a
               witness that what is of the countryside is also created by the Most High!</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C12_eng" n="12" corresp="C12_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">So I am first of all a simple country person, a refugee, and unlearned. I do not know
               how to provide for the future. But this I know for certain, that before I was brought
               low, I was like a stone lying deep in the mud. Then he who is powerful came and in
               his mercy pulled me out, and lifted me up and placed me on the very top of the
                  wall. That is why I must shout
               aloud in return to the Lord for such great good deeds of his, here and now and
               forever, which the human mind cannot measure.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C13_eng" n="13" corresp="C13_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">So be amazed, all you people great and small who fear God! You well-educated people
               in authority, listen and examine this carefully. Who was it who called one as foolish
               as I am from the middle of those who are seen to be wise and
               experienced in law and powerful in speech and in everything? If I am most looked down
               upon, yet he inspired me, before others, so that I would faithfully serve the nations
               with awe and reverence and without blame: the nations to whom the love of Christ
               brought me. His gift was that I would spend my life, if I
               were worthy of it, to serving them in truth and with humility to the end.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C14_eng" n="14" part="I" corresp="C14_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">In the knowledge of this faith in the Trinity, and without letting the dangers
               prevent it, it is right to make known the gift of God and his eternal consolation. It
               is right to spread abroad the name of God faithfully and without fear, so that even
               after my death I may leave something of value to the many thousands of my brothers
               and sisters – the children whom I baptised in the Lord.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C15_eng" n="15" part="F" corresp="C15_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">I didn’t deserve at all that the Lord would grant such great grace, after hardships
               and troubles, after captivity, and after so many years among that people. It was
               something which, when I was young, I never hoped for or even thought of.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C16_eng" n="16" part="I" corresp="C16_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">After I arrived in Ireland, I tended sheep every day, and I prayed frequently during
               the day. More and more the love of God increased, and my sense of awe before God.
               Faith grew, and my spirit was moved, so that in one day I would pray up to one
               hundred times, and at night perhaps the same. I even remained in the woods and on the
               mountain, and I would rise to pray before dawn in snow and ice and rain. I never felt
               the worse for it, and I never felt lazy – as I realise now, the spirit was burning in
               me at that time.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C17_eng" n="17" part="M" corresp="C17_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">It was there one night in my sleep that I heard a voice saying to me: “You have
               fasted well. Very soon you will return to your native country.” Again after a short
               while, I heard a someone saying to me: “Look – your ship is ready.” It was not
               nearby, but a good two hundred miles away. I had never been to the place, nor did I
               know anyone there. So I ran away then, and left the man with whom I had been for six
               years. It was in the strength of God that I went – God who turned the direction of my
               life to good; I feared nothing while I was on the journey to that ship.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C18_eng" n="18" part="M" corresp="C18_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">The day I arrived, the ship was about to leave the place. I said I needed to set sail
               with them, but the captain was not at all pleased. He replied unpleasantly and
               angrily: “Don’t you dare try to come with us.” When I heard that, I left them and
               went back to the hut where I had lodgings. I began to pray while I was going; and
               before I even finished the prayer, I heard one of them shout aloud at me: “Come
               quickly – those men are calling you!” I turned back right away, and they began to say
               to me: “Come – we’ll trust you. Prove you’re our friend in any way you wish.” That
               day, I refused to suck their breasts, because of my reverence for God. They were pagans, and I
               hoped they might come to faith in Jesus Christ. This is how I got to go with them,
               and we set sail right away.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C19_eng" n="19" part="F" corresp="C19_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">After three days we made it to land, and then for twenty eight days we travelled
               through a wilderness. Food ran out, and great hunger came over them. The captain
               turned to me and said: “What about this, Christian? You tell us that your God is
               great and all-powerful – why can’t you pray for us, since we’re in a bad state with
               hunger? There’s no sign of us finding a human being anywhere!” Then I said to them
               with some confidence: “Turn in faith with all your hearts to the Lord my God, because nothing is impossible for him, so that he may put food in your way – even enough to
               make you fully satisfied! He has an abundance everywhere.” With the help of God, this
               is actually what happened! A herd of pigs appeared in the way before our eyes! They
               killed many of them and there they remained for two nights, and were fully restored,
               and the dogs too were filled. Many of them had grown weak and left half-alive by the
               way. After this, they gave the greatest of thanks to God, and I was honoured in their
               eyes. From this day on, they had plenty of food. They also found some wild honey, and
               offered some of it to me. However, one of them said: “This honey must have been
               offered in sacrifice to a god.” Thanks be to God, from then on I tasted none of it.
            </p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C20_eng" n="20" corresp="C20_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">That same night while I was sleeping, Satan strongly put me to the test – I will
               remember it as long as I live! It was as if an enormous rock fell on me, and I lost
               all power in my limbs. Although I knew little about the life of the spirit at the
               time, how was it that I knew to call upon Helias? While these things were happening, I saw the sun rise in the
               sky, and while I was calling “Helias! Helias!” with all my strength, the splendour of
               the sun fell on me; and immediately, all that weight was lifted from me. I believe
               that I was helped by Christ the Lord, and that his spirit cried out for me. I trust
               that it will be like this whenever I am under stress, as the gospel says: “In that
               day, the Lord testifies, it will not be you will speak, but the Spirit of your Father
               who speaks in you.”</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C21_eng" n="21" corresp="C21_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">It happened again after many years that I was taken a prisoner. On the first night I
               was with them, I heard a divine answer saying to me: “You will be with them for two
               months.” This is how it was: on the sixtieth night, the Lord freed me from their
               hands.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C22_eng" n="22" corresp="C22_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N"> While we were still on the journey, the Lord provided food and fire and shelter
               every day until we met some people on the tenth day. As I mentioned above, we
               travelled for twenty eight days through the wilderness. On the very night we met
               people, we ran out of food.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C23_eng" n="23" corresp="C23_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">A few years later I was again with my parents in Britain. They welcomed me as a son,
               and they pleaded with me that, after all the many tribulations I had undergone, I
               should never leave them again. It was while I was there that I saw, in a vision in
               the night, a man whose name was Victoricus
               coming as it were from Ireland with so many letters they could not be counted. He
               gave me one of these, and I read the beginning of the letter, the voice of the Irish
               people. While I was reading out the beginning of the letter, I thought I heard at
               that moment the voice of those who were beside the wood of Voclut, near the western
                  sea. They called out as it were with one voice: “We beg you, holy boy, to come
               and walk again among us.” This touched my heart deeply, and I could not read any
               further; I woke up then. Thanks be to God, after many years the Lord granted them
               what they were calling for.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C24_eng" n="24" corresp="C24_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">Another night – I do not know, God knows, whether it was within me or beside me
               – I heard authoritative words which I could hear but not understand, until at the end
               of the speech it became clear: “The one who gave his life for you, he it is who
               speaks in you”; and I awoke full of joy.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C25_eng" n="25" corresp="C25_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">Another time, I saw in me one who was praying. It was as if I were inside my body,
               and I heard above me, that is, above my inner self. He prayed strongly, with sighs. I
               was amazed and astonished, and pondered who it was who prayed in me; but at the end
               of the prayer, it was clear that it was the Spirit. At this I awoke, and I remembered
               the apostle saying: “The Spirit helps the weaknesses of our prayer; for we do know
               what it is we should pray, but the very Spirit pleads for us with unspeakable sighs,
               which cannot be expressed in words.” And again: “The Lord is our advocate,
               and pleads for us.”</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C26_eng" n="26" corresp="C26_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">One time I was put to the test by some superiors of mine. They came and put my sins
               against my hard work as a bishop. This hit me very hard, so much so that it seemed I
               was about to fall, both here and in eternity. But the Lord in his kindness spared the
               converts and the strangers for the sake of his name, and strongly supported me when I
               was so badly treated. I did not slip into sin and disgrace. I pray that God not hold
               this sin against them.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C27_eng" n="27" corresp="C27_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">They brought up against me after thirty years something I had already confessed
               before I was a deacon. What happened was that, one day when I was feeling anxious and
               low, with a very dear friend of mine I referred to some things I had done one day –
               rather, in one hour – when I was young, before I overcame my weakness. I don’t know –
               God knows – whether I was then fifteen years old at the time, and I did not then
               believe in the living God, not even when I was a child. In fact, I remained in death
               and unbelief until I was reproved strongly, and actually brought low by hunger and
               nakedness daily.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C28_eng" n="28" corresp="C28_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">My defence was that I remained on in Ireland, and that not of my own choosing, until
               I almost perished. However, it was very good for me, since God straightened me out,
               and he prepared me for what I would be today. I was far different then from what I am
               now, and I have care for others, and I have enough to do to save them. In those days
               I did not even have concern for my own welfare.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C29_eng" n="29" corresp="C29_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">So on the day I was accused by those I mentioned above, that same night I saw in a
               vision of the night some writing before my dishonoured face. In the middle of this, I
               heard an answer from God saying to me: “We have seen with displeasure the face of the
               one who was chosen deprived of his good name.” He did not say: “You have seen with
               displeasure”, but “We have seen with displeasure”, as if he were identifying himself
               with me; as he said “He who touches you as it were touches the pupil of my eye.”</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C30_eng" n="30" corresp="C30_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">For that reason, I give thanks to the one who strengthened me in all things, so that he would not impede me in
               the course I had undertaken and from the works also which I had learned from Christ
               my Lord. Rather, I sensed in myself no little strength from him, and my faith passed
               the test before God and people.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C31_eng" n="31" corresp="C31_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">I make bold to say that my conscience does not blame me, now and in the future. I have God
               for witness that I have not told lies in the account I have given you.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C32_eng" n="32" corresp="C32_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">But I grieve more for my very dear friend, that we had to hear such an account – the
               one to whom I entrusted my very soul. I did learn from some brothers before the case
               was heard that he came to my defence in my absence. I was not there at the time, not
               even in Britain, and it was not I who brought up the matter. In fact it was he
               himself who told me from his own mouth: “Look, you are being given the rank of
               bishop.” That is something I did not deserve. How could he then afterwards come to
               disgrace me in public before all, both good and bad, about a matter for which he had
               already freely and joyfully forgiven me, as indeed had God, who is greater than
               all?</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C33_eng" n="33" corresp="C33_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">I have said enough about that. I must take care not to hide the gift of God which he
               has generously given us in the land of my captivity. It was then that I looked for
               him with all my strength, and there I found him, and he protected me from all evils –
               this is what I believe – on account of his Spirit living and working in me to this
               very day. I’m proud to tell again of this. God knows, if it were some other person
               who had said this to me, perhaps I would have said nothing, because of the love of
               Christ.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C34_eng" n="34" corresp="C34_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">So I’ll never stop giving thanks to my God, who kept me faithful in the time of my
               temptation. I can today with confidence offer my soul to Christ my Lord as a living
                  victim. He is the one who defended me in all my
               difficulties. I can say: Who am I, Lord, or what is my calling, that you have worked
               with me with such divine presence? This is how I come to praise and
               magnify your name among the nations all the time, wherever I am, not only in good
               times but in the difficult times too. Whatever comes about for me, good or bad, I
               ought to accept them equally and give thanks to God. He has shown me that I can put
               my faith in him without wavering and without end. However ignorant I am, he has heard
               me, so that in these late days I can dare to undertake such a holy and wonderful
               work. In this way I can imitate somewhat those whom the Lord foretold would announce
               his gospel in witness to all nations before the end of the world. This is what we see
               has been fulfilled. Look at us: we are witnesses that the gospel has been preached
               right out to where there is nobody else there!</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C35_eng" n="35" corresp="C35_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">It’s a long story – to tell each and every deed of mine, or even parts of it. I’ll
               make it short, as I tell of how the good God often freed me from slavery, and from
               twelve dangers which threatened my life, as well as from hidden dangers and from
               things which I have no words to express. I wouldn’t want to hurt my readers! God
               knows all things even before they are done, and I have him as my authority that he
               often gave me warnings in heavenly answers, – me, a wretched orphan!</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C36_eng" n="36" corresp="C36_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">From where did this wisdom come to me, a wisdom which was not in me? I didn’t even know how the number
               of days, much less did I know God. Where did such a great
               and life-giving gift come from then, to know and love God, even at the cost of
               leaving homeland and parents?</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C37_eng" n="37" part="I" corresp="C37_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">And many were the gifts offered to me, along with sorrow and tears. There were those
               whom I offended, even against the wishes of some of my superiors; but, with God
               guiding me, I did not consent nor acquiesce to them. It was not by my own grace, but
               God who overcame it in me, and resisted them all so that I could come to the peoples
               of Ireland to preach the gospel. I bore insults from unbelievers, so that I would
               hear the hatred directed at me for travelling here. I bore many persecutions, even
               chains, so that I could give up my freeborn state for the sake of others. If I be
               worthy, I am ready even to give up my life most willingly here and now for his name.
               It is there that I wish to spend my life until I die, if the Lord should grant it to
               me.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C38_eng" n="38" part="F" corresp="C38_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">I am greatly in debt to God. He gave me such great grace, that through me, many
               people should be born again in God and brought to full life. Also that clerics should
               be ordained everywhere for this people who have lately come to believe, and who the
               Lord has taken from the ends of the earth. This is just what he promised in the past
               through his prophet: “The nations will come to you from the ends of the earth, and
               they will say: How false are the idols our fathers got for themselves, and they are
               of no use whatever.” And
               again: “I have put you as a light to the nations, that you may be their salvation to
               the end of the earth.”</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C39_eng" n="39" corresp="C39_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">It is there that I await his promise – he is the one who never deceives, as is
               repeated in the gospel: “They will come from the east and from the west, and they
               will lie down with Abraham and Isaac and Jacob.” We believe that believing people will come from all over the
               world. </p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C40_eng" n="40" corresp="C40_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">It is right that we should fish well and diligently, as the Lord directs and teaches
               when he says: “Follow me, and I will may you fishers of men.” And again he says through the
               prophets: “Behold, I send many fishers and hunters, says God”; and
               other such sayings. Therefore it is very right that we should cast our nets, so that
               a great multitude and crowd will be taken for God. Also that there should be clerics
               to baptise and encourage a people in need and want. This is what the Lord says in the
               gospel: he warns and teaches in these words: “Go therefore and teach all nations,
               baptising them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit,
               teaching them to observe all that I have commanded you; and behold I am with you all
               days, even to the end of the age.” Again he
               says: “Go out therefore to the whole world and announce the gospel to every creature.
               Whoever believes and is baptised will be saved; whoever does not believe will be
                  condemned.”
               And yet again: “This gospel of the kingdom will be announced all over the world, as
               testimony to all the nations; and then will come the end.” In the same way, the Lord foretold this
               through the prophet as he said: “And it will come about in the last days, says the
               Lord, that I will pour out my Spirit on all flesh, and your sons and your daughters
               will prophesy; your young people will see visions and your older people will dream
               dreams. Indeed, on my servants, men and women, I will pour out my Spirit and they
               will prophesy.” Hosea says: “Those who were not my people, I will call
               my people; and her who has not obtained mercy, I will name the one who has obtained
                  mercy. In the place where it was said: You are not my
               people: there they will be called children of the living God.”</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C41_eng" n="41" corresp="C41_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">How has this happened in Ireland? Never before did they know of God except to serve
               idols and unclean things. But now, they have become the people of the Lord, and are
               called children of God. The sons and daughters of the leaders of the Irish are seen
               to be monks and virgins of Christ!</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C42_eng" n="42" corresp="C42_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">An example is this. There was a blessed Irish woman of noble birth, a most beautiful
               adult whom I baptised. She came to us a few days later for this reason. She told us
               that she had received word from a messenger of God, who advised her that she should
               become a virgin of Christ, and that she should come close to God. Thanks be to God,
               six days later, enthusiastically and well, she took on the life that all virgins of
               God do. Their fathers don’t like this, of course. These women suffer persecution and
               false accusations from their parents, and yet their number grows! We do not know the
               number of our people who were born there. In addition, there are the widows and the
               celibates. Of all these, those held in slavery work hardest – they bear even terror
               and threats, but the Lord gives grace to so many of the women who serve him. Even
               when it is forbidden, they bravely follow his example.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C43_eng" n="43" part="I" corresp="C43_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">I could wish to leave them to go to Britain. I would willingly do this, and am
               prepared for this, as if to visit my home country and my parents. Not only that, but
               I would like to go to Gaul to visit the brothers and to see the faces of the saints
               of my Lord. God knows what I would dearly like to do. But I am bound in the Spirit,
               who assures me that if I were to do this, I would be held guilty. And I fear, also,
               to lose the work which I began – not so much I as Christ the Lord, who told me to
               come here to be with these people for the rest of my life. May the Lord will it, and
               protect me from every wrong path, so that I do not sin before him.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C44_eng" n="44" part="F" corresp="C44_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">I hope to do what I should. I know I cannot trust myself as long as I am in this body
               subject to death. There is one who is strong, who
               tries every day to undermine my faith, and the chastity of genuine religion I have
               chosen to the end of my life for Christ my Lord. The flesh can be an enemy dragging
               towards death, that is, towards doing those enticing things which are against the
               law. I know to some extent how I have not led a perfect life like other believers.
               But I acknowledge this to my Lord, and I do not blush in his sight. I am not telling
               lies: from the time in my youth that I came to know him, the love and reverence for
               God grew in me, and so far, with the Lord’s help, I have kept faith.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C45_eng" n="45" corresp="C45_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">Those who wish may laugh and insult. But I will not be silent, nor will I hide the
               signs and wonders which the Lord has shown me even many years before they came about.
               He knows all things even before the beginning of time.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C46_eng" n="46" corresp="C46_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">So I want to give thanks to God without ceasing. He frequently forgave my lack of
               wisdom and my negligence, and more than once did not become very angry with me, the
               one who was meant to be his helper. I was not quick to accept what he showed me, and
               so the Spirit prompted me. The Lord was merciful to me a thousand thousand times,
               because he saw in me that I was ready, but that I did not know what I should do about
               the state of my life. There were many who forbade this mission. They even told
               stories among themselves behind my back, and the said: “Why does he put himself in
               danger among hostile people who do not know God?” It was not that they were malicious
               – they just did not understand, as I myself can testify, since I was just an
               unlearned country person. Indeed, I was not quick to recognise the grace that was in
               me; I know now what I should have done then.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C47_eng" n="47" corresp="C47_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">Now, therefore, I have informed my brothers and my fellow-servants who believed me,
               because I gave them warning, and I warn them now, in order to strengthen and confirm
               your faith. Oh that you would imitate greater things, and do more powerful
                  things! This will be my glory, since a wise son is the glory of
               his father!</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C48_eng" n="48" corresp="C48_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">You all know, and God knows, how I have lived among you since my youth, in true faith
               and in sincerity of heart. Towards the pagan people too among whom I live, I have
               lived in good faith, and will continue to do so. God knows that I have not been
               devious with even one of them, nor do I think of doing so, for the sake of God and
               his church. I would not want to arouse persecution of them and of all of us; nor
               would I want that the Lord’s name should be blasphemed on account of me; since it is
               written: “Woe to the one through whom the name of the Lord is blasphemed.”</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C49_eng" n="49" corresp="C49_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">I know that I am inexperienced in all things. But still, I have tried to keep a guard
               on myself and for the Christians and virgins of Christ and religious women who were
               giving me small gifts of their own accord. When they would throw some of their
               ornaments on the altar, I would give them back to them. They were hurt at me that I
               would do this. But it was because of the hope of the eternal gift, that I was careful
               in all things, in case unbelievers would trap me or my ministry of service for any
               reason. Nor did I want to give those who could not believe even the slightest reason
               for speaking against me or take my character away.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C50_eng" n="50" part="I" corresp="C50_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">Perhaps, however, when I baptised so many thousands of people, did I hope to receive
               even the smallest payment? If so, tell me, and I will return it to you. Or when the
               Lord ordained clerics everywhere through my poor efforts, and I gave this service to
               them for free, if I asked them to pay even for the cost of my shoes – tell it against
               me, and I will return it to you and more.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C51_eng" n="51" part="F" corresp="C51_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">I spend myself for you, so that you may have me for yours. I have travelled
               everywhere among you for your own sake, in many dangers, and even to the furthest
               parts where nobody lived beyond, and where nobody ever went to baptise and to ordain
               clerics or to bring people to fulfilment. It is only by God’s gift that I diligently
               and most willingly did all of this for your good.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C52_eng" n="52" corresp="C52_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">At times I gave gifts to kings, over and above what I paid to their sons who
               travelled with me. Despite this, they took me and my companions prisoner, and very
               much wanted to kill me, but the time had not yet come. They stole everything they
               found in our possession, and they bound me in iron. On the fourteenth day, the Lord
               set me free from their power; all our possessions were returned to us for God’s sake,
               and for the sake of the close friendship we had had previously.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C53_eng" n="53" corresp="C53_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">You know yourselves how much I expended on those who were the judges in those regions
               which I most frequently visited. I estimate that I gave out not less than the price
               of fifteen persons, so that you might benefit from me, and that I might benefit from
               you in God. I’m not sorry I did it, nor was it even
               enough for me – I still spend, and will spend more. The Lord is powerful, and he can
               grant me still to spend my very self for the sake of your souls.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C54_eng" n="54" corresp="C54_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N"> See now: I call on God as witness in my soul that I tell no lie. Nor would I write to
               you looking for your praise, nor out of greed – it’s not that I hope for honour from
               any of you for myself. It is the honour which is not yet to be seen, but which is
               believed in the heart, which is what gives me satisfaction. The one who gave the
               promise is faithful, and never lies.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C55_eng" n="55" corresp="C55_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">I see that already in this present age the Lord has given me a greatness more than
               could be expected. I was not worthy of this, not the kind of person the Lord would do
               this for, since I know for certain that poverty and calamity are more my style than
               riches and enjoyment. But Christ the Lord became poor for us; I too am wretched and
               unhappy. Even if I were to wish for riches, I do not have them. I am not trying to
               judge myself, since every day there is the chance that I will be killed, or
               surrounded, or be taken into slavery, or some other such happening. But I fear none
               of these things, because of the promises of heaven. I have cast myself into the hands
               of almighty God, who is the ruler of all places, as the prophet says: “Cast your
               concerns on God, and he will sustain you.”</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C56_eng" n="56" corresp="C56_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">Now I commend my soul to my most faithful God. For him I perform the work
               of an ambassador, despite my less than noble condition.
               However, God is not influenced by such personal situations, and he chose me for this
               task so that I would be one servant of his very least important servants.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C57_eng" n="57" corresp="C57_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">So I shall make a return to him for all that he has given to me. But what can I say, or what can I promise to my Lord?
               There is nothing I have that is not his gift to me. But he knows the depths of my
               heart, my very gut feelings! He knows that it is enough that I desire very much, and
               am ready for this, that he would grant me to drink of his chalice, just as he was
               pleased to do for others who loved him.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C58_eng" n="58" part="I" corresp="C58_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">For this reason, may God not let it come about that I would suffer the loss of his
               people who have become his in the furthermost parts of the earth. I pray that God
               give me perseverance, and that he grant me to bear faithful witness to him right up
               to my passing from this life, for the sake of my God.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C59_eng" n="59" part="F" corresp="C59_lat" type="sect" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N"> If I have ever imitated anything good for the sake of my God whom I love, I ask that
               he grant me to be able to shed my blood with these converts and captives – even were
               I to lack a grave for burial, or my dead body were to be miserably torn apart limb
               from limb by dogs or wild beasts, or were the birds of heaven to devour it. I declare
               with certainty that if this were to happen, I would have gained both my soul and my
               body. There is no doubt whatever that we will rise on the appointed day in the
               brightness of the sun, that is, in the glory of Christ Jesus our redeemer. We shall
               be like children of the living God and co-heirs of Christ and
               to be fashioned in his image, since it is from him and through him and in him that we
               are to reign.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C60_eng" n="60" corresp="C60_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">The sun which we see rising for us each day at his command, that sun will never reign
               nor will its splendour continue forever; and all those who adore that sun will come
               to a bad, miserable penalty. We, however, believe in and adore the true sun, that is,
               Christ, who will never perish. Nor will they perish who do his will but they will
               abide forever just as Christ will abide forever. He
               lives with God the Father almighty and with the Holy Spirit before the ages began,
               and now, and for all the ages of ages. Amen.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C61_eng" n="61" corresp="C61_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">Again and again I briefly put before you the words of my confession. I testify in
               truth and in great joy of heart before God and his holy angels that I never had any
               other reason for returning to that nation from which I had earlier escaped, except
               the gospel and God’s promises.</p></div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="C62_eng" n="62" corresp="C62_lat" type="sect" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
            <div type="para" n="1" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p part="N">I pray for those who believe in and have reverence for God. Some of them may happen
               to inspect or come upon this writing which Patrick, a sinner without learning, wrote
               in Ireland. May none of them ever say that whatever little I did or made known to
               please God was done through ignorance. Instead, you can judge and believe in all
               truth that it was a gift of God. This is my confession before I die.</p></div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>