<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/TAN-T.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/TAN.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TAN-T xmlns="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns" TAN-version="2021" id="tag:parkj@textalign.net,2015:bible:matthew:sermon-on-the-mount">
   <head>
      <name>Sermon on the Mount, King James Version of the Bible, 1760 edition</name>
      <master-location href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textalign/TAN-2021/master/examples/sermon-on-the-mount.eng.kjv.1760.xml"/>
      <license which="by 4.0" licensor="park"/>
      <work>
         <IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Sermon_on_the_Mount</IRI>
         <name>Sermon on the Mount</name>
         <desc>Sermon on the Mount, from Matthew 5-7.</desc>
      </work>
      <vocabulary which="bible eng" accessed-when="2019-10-08"/>
      <vocabulary>
         <IRI>tag:parkj@textalign.net,2015:TAN-voc:standard</IRI>
         <name>Keywords for TAN files edited by Jenny Park</name>
         <location href="TAN-voc/park-projects.TAN-voc.xml" accessed-when="2019-10-08"/>
      </vocabulary>
      <source which="kjv 1760"/>
      <inclusion xml:id="lords-prayer">
         <IRI>tag:parkj@textalign.net,2015:bible:matthew:lords-prayer</IRI>
         <name>Matthew's version of the Lord's Prayer, King James Version of the Bible, 1760
            edition</name>
         <location accessed-when="2019-10-09T02:32:50.973-04:00" href="lords-prayer.eng.kjv.1760.xml"/>
      </inclusion>
      <vocabulary-key>
         <person which="Jenny Park" xml:id="park"/>
         <div-type xml:id="v" which="verse (scripture)"/>
      </vocabulary-key>
      <file-resp who="park"/>
      <resp who="park" roles="editor"/>
      <change when="2019-10-08" who="park">Started file.</change>
      <to-do/>
   </head>
   <body xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="5" type="chapter">
         <div n="1" type="v">And seeing the multitudes, he went up into a mountain: and when he was
            set, his disciples came unto him:</div>
         <div n="2" type="v">And he opened his mouth, and taught them, saying,</div>
         <div n="3" type="v">Blessed are the poor in spirit: for theirs is the kingdom of
            heaven.</div>
         <div n="4" type="v">Blessed are they that mourn: for they shall be comforted.</div>
         <div n="5" type="v">Blessed are the meek: for they shall inherit the earth.</div>
         <div n="6" type="v">Blessed are they which do hunger and thirst after righteousness: for
            they shall be filled.</div>
         <div n="7" type="v">Blessed are the merciful: for they shall obtain mercy.</div>
         <div n="8" type="v">Blessed are the pure in heart: for they shall see God.</div>
         <div n="9" type="v">Blessed are the peacemakers: for they shall be called the children of
            God.</div>
         <div n="10" type="v">Blessed are they which are persecuted for righteousness' sake: for
            theirs is the kingdom of heaven.</div>
         <div n="11" type="v">Blessed are ye, when men shall revile you, and persecute you, and
            shall say all manner of evil against you falsely, for my sake.</div>
         <div n="12" type="v">Rejoice, and be exceeding glad: for great is your reward in heaven:
            for so persecuted they the prophets which were before you.</div>
         <div n="13" type="v">Ye are the salt of the earth: but if the salt have lost his savour,
            wherewith shall it be salted? it is thenceforth good for nothing, but to be cast out,
            and to be trodden under foot of men.</div>
         <div n="14" type="v">Ye are the light of the world. A city that is set on an hill cannot be
            hid.</div>
         <div n="15" type="v">Neither do men light a candle, and put it under a bushel, but on a
            candlestick; and it giveth light unto all that are in the house.</div>
         <div n="16" type="v">Let your light so shine before men, that they may see your good works,
            and glorify your Father which is in heaven.</div>
         <div n="17" type="v">Think not that I am come to destroy the law, or the prophets: I am not
            come to destroy, but to fulfil.</div>
         <div n="18" type="v">For verily I say unto you, Till heaven and earth pass, one jot or one
            tittle shall in no wise pass from the law, till all be fulfilled.</div>
         <div n="19" type="v">Whosoever therefore shall break one of these least commandments, and
            shall teach men so, he shall be called the least in the kingdom of heaven: but whosoever
            shall do and teach them, the same shall be called great in the kingdom of heaven.</div>
         <div n="20" type="v">For I say unto you, That except your righteousness shall exceed the
            righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees, ye shall in no case enter into the kingdom
            of heaven.</div>
         <div n="21" type="v">Ye have heard that it was said by them of old time, Thou shalt not
            kill; and whosoever shall kill shall be in danger of the judgment:</div>
         <div n="22" type="v">But I say unto you, That whosoever is angry with his brother without a
            cause shall be in danger of the judgment: and whosoever shall say to his brother, Raca,
            shall be in danger of the council: but whosoever shall say, Thou fool, shall be in
            danger of hell fire.</div>
         <div n="23" type="v">Therefore if thou bring thy gift to the altar, and there rememberest
            that thy brother hath ought against thee;</div>
         <div n="24" type="v">Leave there thy gift before the altar, and go thy way; first be
            reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift.</div>
         <div n="25" type="v">Agree with thine adversary quickly, whiles thou art in the way with
            him; lest at any time the adversary deliver thee to the judge, and the judge deliver
            thee to the officer, and thou be cast into prison.</div>
         <div n="26" type="v">Verily I say unto thee, Thou shalt by no means come out thence, till
            thou hast paid the uttermost farthing.</div>
         <div n="27" type="v">Ye have heard that it was said by them of old time, Thou shalt not
            commit adultery:</div>
         <div n="28" type="v">But I say unto you, That whosoever looketh on a woman to lust after
            her hath committed adultery with her already in his heart.</div>
         <div n="29" type="v">And if thy right eye offend thee, pluck it out, and cast it from thee:
            for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members should perish, and not that thy
            whole body should be cast into hell.</div>
         <div n="30" type="v">And if thy right hand offend thee, cut if off, and cast it from thee:
            for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members should perish, and not that thy
            whole body should be cast into hell.</div>
         <div n="31" type="v">It hath been said, Whosoever shall put away his wife, let him give her
            a writing of divorcement:</div>
         <div n="32" type="v">But I say unto you, That whosoever shall put away his wife, saving for
            the cause of fornication, causeth her to commit adultery: and whosoever shall marry her
            that is divorced committeth adultery.</div>
         <div n="33" type="v">Again, ye have heard that it hath been said by them of old time, Thou
            shalt not forswear thyself, but shalt perform unto the Lord thine oaths:</div>
         <div n="34" type="v">But I say unto you, Swear not at all; neither by heaven; for it is
            God's throne:</div>
         <div n="35" type="v">Nor by the earth; for it is his footstool: neither by Jerusalem; for
            it is the city of the great King.</div>
         <div n="36" type="v">Neither shalt thou swear by thy head, because thou canst not make one
            hair white or black.</div>
         <div n="37" type="v">But let your communication be, Yea, yea; Nay, nay: for whatsoever is
            more than these cometh of evil.</div>
         <div n="38" type="v">Ye have heard that it hath been said, An eye for an eye, and a tooth
            for a tooth:</div>
         <div n="39" type="v">But I say unto you, That ye resist not evil: but whosoever shall smite
            thee on thy right cheek, turn to him the other also.</div>
         <div n="40" type="v">And if any man will sue thee at the law, and take away thy coat, let
            him have thy cloke also.</div>
         <div n="41" type="v">And whosoever shall compel thee to go a mile, go with him twain.</div>
         <div n="42" type="v">Give to him that asketh thee, and from him that would borrow of thee
            turn not thou away.</div>
         <div n="43" type="v">Ye have heard that it hath been said, Thou shalt love thy neighbour,
            and hate thine enemy.</div>
         <div n="44" type="v">But I say unto you, Love your enemies, bless them that curse you, do
            good to them that hate you, and pray for them which despitefully use you, and persecute
            you;</div>
         <div n="45" type="v">That ye may be the children of your Father which is in heaven: for he
            maketh his sun to rise on the evil and on the good, and sendeth rain on the just and on
            the unjust.</div>
         <div n="46" type="v">For if ye love them which love you, what reward have ye? do not even
            the publicans the same?</div>
         <div n="47" type="v">And if ye salute your brethren only, what do ye more than others? do
            not even the publicans so?</div>
         <div n="48" type="v">Be ye therefore perfect, even as your Father which is in heaven is
            perfect.</div></div>
      <div n="6" type="chapter">
         <div n="1" type="v">Take heed that ye do not your alms before men, to be seen of them:
            otherwise ye have no reward of your Father which is in heaven.</div>
         <div n="2" type="v">Therefore when thou doest thine alms, do not sound a trumpet before
            thee, as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the streets, that they may have
            glory of men. Verily I say unto you, They have their reward.</div>
         <div n="3" type="v">But when thou doest alms, let not thy left hand know what thy right
            hand doeth:</div>
         <div n="4" type="v">That thine alms may be in secret: and thy Father which seeth in secret
            himself shall reward thee openly.</div>
         <div n="5" type="v">And when thou prayest, thou shalt not be as the hypocrites are: for
            they love to pray standing in the synagogues and in the corners of the streets, that
            they may be seen of men. Verily I say unto you, They have their reward.</div>
         <div n="6" type="v">But thou, when thou prayest, enter into thy closet, and when thou hast
            shut thy door, pray to thy Father which is in secret; and thy Father which seeth in
            secret shall reward thee openly.</div>
         <div n="7" type="v">But when ye pray, use not vain repetitions, as the heathen do: for they
            think that they shall be heard for their much speaking.</div>
         <div n="8" type="v">Be not ye therefore like unto them: for your Father knoweth what things
            ye have need of, before ye ask him.</div>
         <div n="9" type="v">After this manner therefore pray ye:</div>
         <div include="lords-prayer"/>
         <div n="14" type="v">For if ye forgive men their trespasses, your heavenly Father will also
            forgive you:</div>
         <div n="15" type="v">But if ye forgive not men their trespasses, neither will your Father
            forgive your trespasses.</div>
         <div n="16" type="v">Moreover when ye fast, be not, as the hypocrites, of a sad
            countenance: for they disfigure their faces, that they may appear unto men to fast.
            Verily I say unto you, They have their reward.</div>
         <div n="17" type="v">But thou, when thou fastest, anoint thine head, and wash thy
            face;</div>
         <div n="18" type="v">That thou appear not unto men to fast, but unto thy Father which is in
            secret: and thy Father, which seeth in secret, shall reward thee openly.</div>
         <div n="19" type="v">Lay not up for yourselves treasures upon earth, where moth and rust
            doth corrupt, and where thieves break through and steal:</div>
         <div n="20" type="v">But lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor
            rust doth corrupt, and where thieves do not break through nor steal:</div>
         <div n="21" type="v">For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also.</div>
         <div n="22" type="v">The light of the body is the eye: if therefore thine eye be single,
            thy whole body shall be full of light.</div>
         <div n="23" type="v">But if thine eye be evil, thy whole body shall be full of darkness. If
            therefore the light that is in thee be darkness, how great is that darkness!</div>
         <div n="24" type="v">No man can serve two masters: for either he will hate the one, and
            love the other; or else he will hold to the one, and despise the other. Ye cannot serve
            God and mammon.</div>
         <div n="25" type="v">Therefore I say unto you, Take no thought for your life, what ye shall
            eat, or what ye shall drink; nor yet for your body, what ye shall put on. Is not the
            life more than meat, and the body than raiment?</div>
         <div n="26" type="v">Behold the fowls of the air: for they sow not, neither do they reap,
            nor gather into barns; yet your heavenly Father feedeth them. Are ye not much better
            than they?</div>
         <div n="27" type="v">Which of you by taking thought can add one cubit unto his
            stature?</div>
         <div n="28" type="v">And why take ye thought for raiment? Consider the lilies of the field,
            how they grow; they toil not, neither do they spin:</div>
         <div n="29" type="v">And yet I say unto you, That even Solomon in all his glory was not
            arrayed like one of these.</div>
         <div n="30" type="v">Wherefore, if God so clothe the grass of the field, which to day is,
            and to morrow is cast into the oven, shall he not much more clothe you, O ye of little
            faith?</div>
         <div n="31" type="v">Therefore take no thought, saying, What shall we eat? or, What shall
            we drink? or, Wherewithal shall we be clothed?</div>
         <div n="32" type="v">(For after all these things do the Gentiles seek:) for your heavenly
            Father knoweth that ye have need of all these things.</div>
         <div n="33" type="v">But seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his righteousness; and all
            these things shall be added unto you.</div>
         <div n="34" type="v">Take therefore no thought for the morrow: for the morrow shall take
            thought for the things of itself. Sufficient unto the day is the evil
         thereof.</div></div>
      <div n="7" type="chapter">
         <div n="1" type="v">Judge not, that ye be not judged.</div>
         <div n="2" type="v">For with what judgment ye judge, ye shall be judged: and with what
            measure ye mete, it shall be measured to you again.</div>
         <div n="3" type="v">And why beholdest thou the mote that is in thy brother's eye, but
            considerest not the beam that is in thine own eye?</div>
         <div n="4" type="v">Or how wilt thou say to thy brother, Let me pull out the mote out of
            thine eye; and, behold, a beam is in thine own eye?</div>
         <div n="5" type="v">Thou hypocrite, first cast out the beam out of thine own eye; and then
            shalt thou see clearly to cast out the mote out of thy brother's eye.</div>
         <div n="6" type="v">Give not that which is holy unto the dogs, neither cast ye your pearls
            before swine, lest they trample them under their feet, and turn again and rend
            you.</div>
         <div n="7" type="v">Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it
            shall be opened unto you:</div>
         <div n="8" type="v">For every one that asketh receiveth; and he that seeketh findeth; and
            to him that knocketh it shall be opened.</div>
         <div n="9" type="v">Or what man is there of you, whom if his son ask bread, will he give
            him a stone?</div>
         <div n="10" type="v">Or if he ask a fish, will he give him a serpent?</div>
         <div n="11" type="v">If ye then, being evil, know how to give good gifts unto your
            children, how much more shall your Father which is in heaven give good things to them
            that ask him?</div>
         <div n="12" type="v">Therefore all things whatsoever ye would that men should do to you, do
            ye even so to them: for this is the law and the prophets.</div>
         <div n="13" type="v">Enter ye in at the strait gate: for wide is the gate, and broad is the
            way, that leadeth to destruction, and many there be which go in thereat:</div>
         <div n="14" type="v">Because strait is the gate, and narrow is the way, which leadeth unto
            life, and few there be that find it.</div>
         <div n="15" type="v">Beware of false prophets, which come to you in sheep's clothing, but
            inwardly they are ravening wolves.</div>
         <div n="16" type="v">Ye shall know them by their fruits. Do men gather grapes of thorns, or
            figs of thistles?</div>
         <div n="17" type="v">Even so every good tree bringeth forth good fruit; but a corrupt tree
            bringeth forth evil fruit.</div>
         <div n="18" type="v">A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, neither can a corrupt tree
            bring forth good fruit.</div>
         <div n="19" type="v">Every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, and cast
            into the fire.</div>
         <div n="20" type="v">Wherefore by their fruits ye shall know them.</div>
         <div n="21" type="v">Not every one that saith unto me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the
            kingdom of heaven; but he that doeth the will of my Father which is in heaven.</div>
         <div n="22" type="v">Many will say to me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not prophesied in
            thy name? and in thy name have cast out devils? and in thy name done many wonderful
            works?</div>
         <div n="23" type="v">And then will I profess unto them, I never knew you: depart from me,
            ye that work iniquity.</div>
         <div n="24" type="v">Therefore whosoever heareth these sayings of mine, and doeth them, I
            will liken him unto a wise man, which built his house upon a rock:</div>
         <div n="25" type="v">And the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and
            beat upon that house; and it fell not: for it was founded upon a rock.</div>
         <div n="26" type="v">And every one that heareth these sayings of mine, and doeth them not,
            shall be likened unto a foolish man, which built his house upon the sand:</div>
         <div n="27" type="v">And the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and
            beat upon that house; and it fell: and great was the fall of it.</div>
         <div n="28" type="v">And it came to pass, when Jesus had ended these sayings, the people
            were astonished at his doctrine:</div>
         <div n="29" type="v">For he taught them as one having authority, and not as the
            scribes.</div></div>
   </body>
</TAN-T>