<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="tan-applications" version="5.0"><title>TAN Applications</title><para>Standard TAN applications are designed to take TAN or TEI files and create output
               that allows users to study particular aspects of the text through interaction,
               statistics, and visualization. These are advanced, complex programs, and not all the
               intended features may have been implemented. </para><para>Because of their power, these applications have numerous parameters for
               configuration. You are encouraged to read closely the documentation in the
               application to determine how to make the application work for your particular
               goals.</para><para>Each section below is generated automatically from the master file that drives the
               process. Any global parameters that are referred to in the discussion are explained in
               the file itself. </para><section xml:id="Diff_"><title>Diff+</title><para><emphasis>Location: </emphasis><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="../applications/Diff+/Diff+.xsl">applications/Diff+/Diff+.xsl</link></para><para> Version 2021-09-06 </para><para> Take any number of versions of a text, compare them, and view and study all the text
        differences in an HTML page. The HTML output allows you to see precisely where one version
        differs from the other. A small Javascript library allows you to change focus, remove
        versions, and explore statistics that show quantitatively how close the versions are to each
        other. Parameters allow you to make normalizations before making the comparison, and to weigh
        statistics accordingly. This application has been used not only for individual comparisons,
        but for more demanding needs: to analyze changes in documents passing through a multistep
        editorial workflow, to compare the quality of OCR results, and to study the relationship
        between ancient/medieval manuscripts (stemmatology).</para><para> Examples of output:<itemizedlist><listitem><para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://textalign.net/output/CFR-2017-title1-vol1-compared.xml"><code>https://textalign.net/output/CFR-2017-title1-vol1-compared.xml</code></link>
            XML master output file, comparing four years of the United States Code of Federal Regulations,
            vol. 1</para></listitem><listitem><para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://textalign.net/output/CFR-2017-title1-vol1-compared.html"><code>https://textalign.net/output/CFR-2017-title1-vol1-compared.html</code></link>
            HTML comparison of four years of the United States Code of Federal Regulations, vol. 1</para></listitem><listitem><para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://textalign.net/output/diff-grc-2021-02-08-five-versions.html"><code>https://textalign.net/output/diff-grc-2021-02-08-five-versions.html</code></link>
            Comparison of results from four OCR processes against a benchmark,
            classical Greek</para></listitem><listitem><para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://textalign.net/clio/darwin-3diff.html"><code>https://textalign.net/clio/darwin-3diff.html</code></link>
            Comparison of three editions of Darwin's works, sample</para></listitem><listitem><para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://textalign.net/clio/hom-01-coll-ignore-uv.html"><code>https://textalign.net/clio/hom-01-coll-ignore-uv.html</code></link>
            Comparison of five versions of Griffolini's translation of John Chrysostom's Homily 1 on 
            the Gospel of John
    </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para> This master stylesheet is the public interface for the application. The parameters you will most
      likely want to change are listed and documented below, to help you customize the application to suit
      your needs. If you are relatively new to XSLT, or TAN applications, see Using TAN Applications and
      Utilities in the TAN Guidelines for general instructions. If you want to avoid changing the master
      application file, use the accompanying configuration file. Or make a copy of this file and edit and
      run it directly. Or create and configure a transformation scenario in Oxygen, defining the relevant
      parameters as you like. If you are comfortable with XSLT, try creating your own stylesheet, then
      import this one, and customize the process. To access the code base, follow the link in the
      <code>&lt;xsl:include&gt;</code> at the bottom of this file. </para><para><emphasis role="bold"> Description </emphasis></para><para> This is a MIRU Stylesheet (MIRU = Main Input Resolved URIs) </para><para><emphasis>Primary input:</emphasis> any XML file, including this one (input is ignored) </para><para><emphasis>Secondary input:</emphasis> one or more files </para><para><emphasis>Primary output:</emphasis> perhaps diagnostics </para><para><emphasis>Secondary output:</emphasis> for each detectable language in the secondary input: (1) an XML file with
      the results of <code><link linkend="function-diff">tan:diff()</link></code> or <code><link linkend="function-collate">tan:collate()</link></code>, infused with select statistical analyses; (2) a
      rendering of #1 in an interactive, visually engaging HTML form </para><para><emphasis>Nota bene:</emphasis> </para><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>This application is useful only if the input files have different versions of the same text 
        in the same language. </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The XML output is a straightforward result of <code><link linkend="function-diff">tan:diff()</link></code> or <code><link linkend="function-collate">tan:collate()</link></code>, perhaps wrapped by
        an element that also includes prepended statistical analysis. </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The HTML output has been designed to work with specific JavaScript and CSS files, and the HTML 
        output will not render correctly unless you have set up dependencies correctly. Currently, the 
        HTML output is directed to the TAN output subdirectory, with the HTML pointing to the appropriate
        javascript and CSS files in the js and css directories. </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para><emphasis role="bold"> Warning: certain features have yet to be implemented</emphasis></para><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Revise process that reinfuses a class 1 file with a diff/collate into a standard extra
        TAN function.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Add parameter to allow serialization of input XML, for closer comparison of XML structures.
    </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para> This application currently just scratches the surface of what is possible. New features are
        planned! Some desiderata:<orderedlist><listitem><para>Support a single TAN-A as the catalyst or MIRU provider, allowing <code><link linkend="element-alias">&lt;alias&gt;</link></code> to define the groups.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Support MIRUs that point to non-TAN files, e.g., plain text, docx, xml.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Allow one to decide whether Venn diagrams should adjust the common area or not.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Enhance options on statistics.
    </para></listitem></orderedlist></para></section><section xml:id="Parabola"><title>Parabola</title><para><emphasis>Location: </emphasis><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="../applications/Parabola/Parabola.xsl">applications/Parabola/Parabola.xsl</link></para><para> Version 2021-07-20</para><para> This application allows you to take a library of TAN/TEI files with multiple versions of
      each work and present them in an interactive HTML page.</para><para> This master stylesheet is the public interface for the application. The parameters you will most
      likely want to change are listed and documented below, to help you customize the application to suit
      your needs. If you are relatively new to XSLT, or TAN applications, see Using TAN Applications and
      Utilities in the TAN Guidelines for general instructions. If you want to avoid changing the master
      application file, use the accompanying configuration file. Or make a copy of this file and edit and
      run it directly. Or create and configure a transformation scenario in Oxygen, defining the relevant
      parameters as you like. If you are comfortable with XSLT, try creating your own stylesheet, then
      import this one, and customize the process. To access the code base, follow the link in the
      <code>&lt;xsl:include&gt;</code> at the bottom of this file. </para><para><emphasis>Examples of output:</emphasis> <itemizedlist><listitem><para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://textalign.net/output/aristotle-categories-ref-bekker-page-col-line.html"><code>http://textalign.net/output/aristotle-categories-ref-bekker-page-col-line.html</code></link>
         Aristotle, Categories, in eight versions, six languages</para></listitem><listitem><para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://textalign.net/output/cpg%204425.TAN-A-div-2018-03-09.html"><code>https://textalign.net/output/cpg%204425.TAN-A-div-2018-03-09.html</code></link>
         Homilies on the Gospel of John, John Chrysostom, four versions, two languages</para></listitem><listitem><para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://evagriusponticus.net/cpg2430/cpg2430-full-for-reading.html"><code>https://evagriusponticus.net/cpg2430/cpg2430-full-for-reading.html</code></link>
         The Praktikos by Evagrius of Pontus, three languages, with Bible quotations</para></listitem><listitem><para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://textalign.net/quran/quran.ara+grc+syr+lat+deu+eng.html"><code>https://textalign.net/quran/quran.ara+grc+syr+lat+deu+eng.html</code></link>
         Qur'an in eighteen versions, six languages</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para><emphasis role="bold"> Description </emphasis></para><para><emphasis>Primary input:</emphasis> a TAN-A file </para><para><emphasis>Secondary input:</emphasis> its sources expanded </para><para><emphasis>Primary output:</emphasis> an interactive HTML page with the versions of the chosen work grouped and arranged
      in parallel, with annotations </para><para><emphasis>Secondary output:</emphasis> none </para><para> This flagship TAN application was the catalyst for TAN itself. It was developed not only for
      highly polished, finalized web publication, but to support complex editorial processes. The impetus
      was a project of five scholars translating into English an ancient text that survives only
      fragmentarily in its original Greek, and that was translated into Syriac several times. The team
      intended to translate into English the Greek fragments that survive, as well as the Syriac
      translations, and to do so with rigorous consistency. In passages where the author (Evagrius of
      Pontus) quoted from Scripture or Aristotle, they needed to be able to consult the Greek or Syriac
      text behind the quoted source. Such demands required a shared digital infrastructure to coordinate
      roughly forty different versions, including the team's working English translations, which were
      changing week to week. Parabola was indispensible.
 </para><para> Nota bene:<itemizedlist><listitem><para>This application has many fine-tuned configuration options. Read through the whole file
      to see what is available.</para></listitem><listitem><para>This application processes a single work, assumed to be that of the first <code><link linkend="element-source">&lt;source&gt;</link></code> in the
      catalyzing TAN-A file. If you want a different source, move the relevant <code><link linkend="element-source">&lt;source&gt;</link></code> to the first
      position.
   </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para><emphasis role="bold"> Warning: certain features have yet to be implemented </emphasis></para><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Simplify the routine. This was converted from an inferior workflow, and still takes too many
      passes to get to the output. </para></listitem><listitem><para>Annotations need a lot of work. They should be placed into the merge early. In fact, the whole
      workflow needs to be revised, with most structural work finished before attempting to convert to
      HTML. </para></listitem><listitem><para>Develop output option using nested HTML divs, to parallel the existing output that uses HTML
      tables </para></listitem><listitem><para>Integrate diff/collate into cells, on both the global and local level. </para></listitem><listitem><para>Develop the css bar to allow users to click source id labels on and off. </para></listitem><listitem><para>Add labels for divs higher than version wrappers. </para></listitem><listitem><para>Consider merging based upon the resolved file, not its expansion. </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section xml:id="TAN_Out"><title>TAN Out</title><para><emphasis>Location: </emphasis><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="../applications/TAN%20Out/TAN%20Out.xsl">applications/TAN%20Out/TAN%20Out.xsl</link></para><para> Version 2021-09-06 </para><para> This utility exports a TAN or TEI file to other media. Currently only HTML is supported, optimized
      for JavaScript and CSS within the output/js and output/css directories in the TAN file structure. </para><para> This utility quickly renders a TAN or TEI file as HTML. It has been optimized for JavaScript and CSS
      within the output/js and output/css in the TAN file structure. </para><para> This master stylesheet is the public interface for the application. The parameters you will most
      likely want to change are listed and documented below, to help you customize the application to suit
      your needs. If you are relatively new to XSLT, or TAN applications, see Using TAN Applications and
      Utilities in the TAN Guidelines for general instructions. If you want to avoid changing the master
      application file, use the accompanying configuration file. Or make a copy of this file and edit and
      run it directly. Or create and configure a transformation scenario in Oxygen, defining the relevant
      parameters as you like. If you are comfortable with XSLT, try creating your own stylesheet, then
      import this one, and customize the process. To access the code base, follow the link in the
      <code>&lt;xsl:include&gt;</code> at the bottom of this file. </para><para><emphasis role="bold"> Description </emphasis></para><para><emphasis>Primary input:</emphasis> any TAN or TEI file </para><para><emphasis>Secondary input:</emphasis> none </para><para><emphasis>Primary output:</emphasis> if no destination filename is specified, an HTML file </para><para><emphasis>Secondary output:</emphasis> if a destination filename is specified, an HTML file at the target location </para><para> Nota bene:<itemizedlist><listitem><para>This application can be used to generate primary or secondary output, depending upon how
      parameters are configured (see below).
   </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para><emphasis role="bold"> Warning: certain features have yet to be implemented </emphasis></para><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Need to wholly overhaul the default CSS and JavaScript files in output/css and output/js </para></listitem><listitem><para>Need to build parameters to allow users to drop elements from the HTML DOM.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Need to enrich output message with parameter settings.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Need to support export to odt. </para></listitem><listitem><para>Need to support export to docx. </para></listitem><listitem><para>Need to support export to plain text.
   </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section xml:id="Tangram"><title>Tangram</title><para><emphasis>Location: </emphasis><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="../applications/Tangram/Tangram.xsl">applications/Tangram/Tangram.xsl</link></para><para> This application searches for and scores clusters of words shared across two groups of texts, allowing
      you to look for quotations, paraphrases, or shared topics. When configured correctly, Tangram can
      also find idioms and collocations. Each input file, which may come in a variety of formats (TAN,
      TEI, other XML formats, plain text, Word documents) must be assigned to one or both of two groups,
      each group representing a work. Members of a work-group can be from different languages. Users can
      specify how many ngrams ("words") should be found, and how far apart they can be from each other.
      Ngram order is disregarded (e.g., ngram "shear", "blue", "sheep" would match ngram "sheep", "blue",
      "shear"). Tangram first normalizes and tokenizes each text according to language rules. Each token
      is converted to one or more aliases. If lexico-morphological data is available through a TAN-A-lm
      file, or if there is a TAN-A-lm language library for the language of the text being processed, a
      token may be replaced by multiple lexemes (e.g., "rung" would attract aliases "ring" and "rung");
      otherwise, a case-insensitive generic form of the word is used. Then each text in group 1 is
      compared to each text in group 2 that shares the same language. For each pair of texts, Tangram
      identifies clusters of tokens that share the same alias. It then consolidates adjacent clusters of
      ngrams, and scores the results based upon several criteria. Grouped clusters are then converted
      into a primitive TAN-A file consisting of claims that identify parallel passages of each pair of
      texts, and the output is rendered as sortable HTML, to facilitate better study of the results.
      Tangram was written primarily to support quotation detection in ancient Greek and Latin texts,
      which has rather demanding requirements. Because of these objectives, Tangram frequently operates
      in quadratic or cubic time, so can be quite time-consuming to run. A feature allows the user to
      save intermediate stages as temporary files, to reduce processing time. </para><para> Version 2021-09-06</para><para> This master stylesheet is the public interface for the application. The parameters you will most
      likely want to change are listed and documented below, to help you customize the application to suit
      your needs. If you are relatively new to XSLT, or TAN applications, see Using TAN Applications and
      Utilities in the TAN Guidelines for general instructions. If you want to avoid changing the master
      application file, use the accompanying configuration file. Or make a copy of this file and edit and
      run it directly. Or create and configure a transformation scenario in Oxygen, defining the relevant
      parameters as you like. If you are comfortable with XSLT, try creating your own stylesheet, then
      import this one, and customize the process. To access the code base, follow the link in the
      <code>&lt;xsl:include&gt;</code> at the bottom of this file. </para><para><emphasis role="bold"> Description </emphasis></para><para><emphasis>Primary input:</emphasis> any XML file, including this one (input is ignored) </para><para><emphasis>Secondary input:</emphasis> one or more files allocated to two groups; perhaps temporary files; perhaps
      TAN-A-lm files, either associated with secondary input, or part of a language catalog </para><para><emphasis>Primary output:</emphasis> perhaps diagnostics </para><para><emphasis>Secondary output:</emphasis> (1) an XML file with TAN-A claims identifying quotations or parallels, with the
      most likely at the top; (2) an HTML file that renders #1 in a more legible format. </para><para><emphasis role="bold"> Warning: certain features have yet to be implemented</emphasis></para><para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Support the method pioneered by Shmidman, Koppel, and Porat:
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1602.08715v2"><code>https://arxiv.org/abs/1602.08715v2</code></link> </para></listitem><listitem><para>Make sure texts run against themselves work.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Incorporate simpler tablesorter javascript
   </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para><emphasis>Nota bene:</emphasis> </para><para> <itemizedlist><listitem><para>This application is one of the most experimental, and may not perform as expected. It has been 
      successfully tested on several dozen classical Greek texts. </para></listitem><listitem><para>A file may be placed in both groups, to explore cases of self-quotation or 
      repetition. </para></listitem><listitem><para>This process can take a very long time for lengthy texts, particuarly at the stage where a 1gram 
      gets added to an Ngram, because the process takes quadratic time. Many messages could appear during
      <code>tan:add-1gram()</code>, updating progress through perhaps long routines. It is recommended that you save
      intermediate steps, to avoid having to repeat steps on subsequent runs. </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para><emphasis>Processing time example:</emphasis> two texts in group 1 of about 4.4K and 2.6K words against a single
      text in group 2 of about 137K words took 319 seconds to build up to a set of unconsolidated token
      aliases. One text from group 1 had an associated TAN-A-lm annotation and the text from group 2 did
      as well. There was a TAN-A-lm library associated with the language (Greek). When the program was
      run again without changing parameters, it took only 11 seconds to get to that same stage, because
      of the saved temporary files. That same set of texts took 1,219 seconds (20 minutes) to develop
      into a 3gram, with chops at common Greek stop words and skipping the most common 1% token aliases.
      When run again, based on temporary files, it took only 23 seconds. That is, saving intermediate
      steps could save you hours of time. </para></section></section>